He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
in our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey greetings, Dragon Slayer's,
Giant Killers and Detonators of Demon's Serpent's,
Christ has risen.
You're listening to the 139th episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
coming to you from the bustling North Carolinian
metropolis of Raleigh for the first time
from the brand new three-marter studio,
the veritable Versailles of Vocal Vigor,
the Palace of Podcasting.
So, when you say the Versailles of Vocal Figure, there's literally a ballroom upstairs called the Murray Antoinette ballroom, like I'm not even joking.
Did you come to some sort of agreement to use the space?
Something like that, yes.
So, you realize the Treaty of Versailles was bungled and resulted in millions of deaths in the Second World War?
It's true.
Let's try to- I don't know why you'd want to-
invoke that kind of dark history here at the beginning.
I mean, my last location was perched precariously over top of a disused gateway to the underworld.
So maybe here I'm supposed to stand,
afford the guillotine.
I mean, there's no, I'm not talking.
Okay.
French Revolution.
It's all one century.
It's all one World War two mid-to-one century.
I'm just telling you,
We have deeper issues here than just you know
you're making an untoward reference.
Comparing.
Singswing, saver the sting, Madame Gia-teen.
Comparing your new studio at the agreement,
to found it to one of the most regrettable bungalings
in 20th century world history.
But anyway, well, I mean, yes,
well, you father Steven D'Young,
our needy in the swampy muck of Lafayette Louisiana.
So is that better?
Probably.
this last time.
you can try to connect it to the War of 1812 in the Battle of New Orleans, I guess somehow,
but I mean, then it's going to be a strain. Yep. Yep. Well, we are actually a much bigger debacle.
You know, other things happen at Versailles father, not a whole of it is treaties.
Not. Not really. Yeah. Okay. So anyway, anyway, we are alive. We're alive. And that means that Mike
like Hadookin again will be taking your calls.
starting in the second half.
So have you ever wondered what happened to the apostles
after the acts of the apostles?
It turns out that there are various texts
from the early church, which tell stories
about the apostles and what they did next
and some of them are pretty wild.
And we all know that wild stories
are what you come here for.
So that's what you're gonna get tonight.
But first we're gonna go all the way back to
well, not Genesis, right?
Where we start out.
I mean, we could.
Why not?
We could, we could go-
Genesis or Stone Age or something if you really want to, I can figure out a way to do that.
And yeah, the wildness of the stories will probably end up being good news for those
of you who are upset about the number of ads that this show has on YouTube.
Because I'm pretty sure we're getting demonetized with this one.
Out about eight different counts.
You're going to give poor Simon Hartburn.
Yes.
People are going to be clipping this and sending it to our bishops.
Yeah.
for today.
That's right. I hope so. I hope so. So where are we starting if it's not Genesis?
Well, we will start with the canonical acts of the Apostles.
Because what we're going to be talking about most of tonight are non-canonical acts of various
and sundry apostles. So there's a
of course just the one book, the Acts of the Apostles,
in the New Testament, that picks up,
well, really begins with a retelling of Christ's ascension,
and then moves on in history from there.
Does not move that far in terms of consecutive time, right?
And then that is the end of narrative, really,
for the New Testament.
I mean, technically, there are little bits of narrative
surrounding St. John's vision in Revelation.
but that...
Yeah, and there's some clues from St. Paul's epistles, but it's not. Yeah, he refers to things that happen. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
But in terms of actual, just narrative storytelling, that's that's sort of the last book. But included among the various non-canonical texts related to the New Testament,
is a whole genre.
of acts of the apostles that are compiled from traditions about different apostles after
the take place mostly after the Book of Acts, as you mentioned. Then at least one case there may
maybe a little bit of overlap time wise.
But we're going to be talking about four of those books.
this evening. There are some others and there are some books that sort of blur the line,
genre wise, right? For example, there are a lot of gnostic texts that purport to be written
by various apostles that will have like some narrative elements about that apostle as
as well as stuff about Jesus or cookie visions
or other Nostek nonsense.
in them. So there's that kind of thing. There's a whole genre of literature as
cribed to St. James, the brother of the Lord, in particular. Yeah. And that's not
what this episode is about. People do get excited about that stuff. But yes, but
that's another set of stuff. Some of that is not sick and some of it isn't.
So there's there is
other stuff there. So the four texts we're going to talk about tonight do not exhaust everything that could
be shoehorned into this category. But the four texts we're going to mainly focus on are four texts that
have historical importance as indicated by the number of copies we still have, for example,
and the number of translations.
and the different languages we have, that they played some part in one of them, in particular,
played a part in one of the ecumenical councils. All these four are found on
on St. Nicholas, the confessor of Constantinople, his list of texts in the texts that are
not read publicly in the church, but are good to be read privately.
Yeah, which is apocrypha. That's what apocrypha are.
Yes, it means private. Does it mean secret or hidden?
It means private.
A Sotaric secret wisdom.
Yes.
And so that's all the way in the beginning of the ninth century.
The church still considered these texts to be
worthwhile reading it to
contain important traditions. A lot of these texts contain the earliest written version
of some of these traditions that still exists. We'll get into that while we're phrasing
it that way in a little bit. But with traditions that are also attested to elsewhere outside
of these texts. But so that's why we're talking about the that's why these four texts in
particular.
I think are especially worth talking about compared to some of the others.
But so to sort of frame this whole discussion, we kind of want to start with the canonical
book of the Acts of the Apostles.
And the Acts of the Apostles is kind of a weird book in terms of the New Testament canon.
Yeah.
stop to think about it.
So, let's all pause for a moment of silence, please.
Let's all think about it.
So, for example, right, it's in our epistle book, or the Apostle, the book of the Apostle,
the Apostolic One, or Apostolic One.
Apostolus.
It is it is in there
whatever fake acts that you want to affect. But it's of a different fundamentally different genre
than everything else in that book. Everything else in that book isn't a pistol.
That's why we so often refer to it as the epistle book, right? Yeah.
Because that's the vast majority of what's in there. But the book of acts is also in there. And if
if you've been attending liturgy.
Since Paska you have heard readings from the acts of the Apostles. Yeah, yep, very epistle time, but
Genro wise
Right, here's the genre of text
It's basically the same genre as the gospels
Yeah, it's it's narrative
what next and
And more to the point, it's volume two of a two-volume work with the gospel.
of Saint Luke. Now did Luke and Acts ever circulate together like as a single text that we know of?
They did. In fact, the variations that we have are variations across Luke and Acts. So there's
what's called Western Luke Acts that's a whole set of text variants. What they're spread across
both the Gospel of Luke and the Book of Acts.
So yeah, they didn't circulate independently as far as we could tell.
Yeah.
Nevertheless, right?
We have liturgically severed acts from Luke functionally.
Right?
And that's because even though genre wise, it's the same genre as St. Luke's Gospel,
Obviously, St. Luke's Gospel has a different at least-
on the surface, main character. Right? So the main character very directly and on the surface
of St. Luke's Gospel is Christ. Right? Now you could ultimately say the same thing about the
book of Acts. We'll get to that in a minute, but that's less of the surface. Right? The person
who's being talked about just on a surface reading of the book of Acts, if you read it out loud,
for most of the book of access, St. Paul, but not all of it.
Just like the last two thirds or so.
And the first third, there's a whole bunch of different people, say Peter, say Philip,
say Stephen, that are sort of in the foreground, with Christ in the background all the way through.
This is also, it's kind of a challenging book to the way many of us may have been taught
to read
the scriptures. So for example, one one very common view of the Old Testament that you will
hear is that well the Old Testament is just all of these shadows and types that are pointing
us to Jesus, right? And applied within that is that sort of oh well now that we have Jesus
and we have the gospels, Christ has revealed all these things clearly. Now, right the Old
test of it at the type.
So the shadows are kind of obsolete because now we have the fullness and everything.
And so soft Marcianism.
Yeah.
And so then when you read the Old Testament narratives, right,
their narratives about people other than Jesus of Nazareth, right?
Uh, again, at least on the surface, you could say it's all ultimately about him,
but on the surface, right, we're reading about King David or reading about King Saul or Ezra or whomever,
Right.
But their scene is being a type of, they point us to Christ.
So they'll talk about David and Goliath in terms of, right, David as, you know, the
future king, we represent of Christ, Goliath, representing, you know, the devil or the enemies
of God and, right.
And this kind of typological reading.
I'm not saying there's something wrong with that kind of typological reading, right.
That's it.
idea that that's all that's going on there. Right? That's all that's going on there. And so that
the details of the information and even the people themselves, like Abraham, Isaac and Jacob
and Moses and whoever for the Old Testament are now sort of obsolete because we just, you know,
what we just need Christ, right? We have Christ. Christ has got Himself. We don't need these images
and stuff, kind of then invokes the question.
and so why the book of Acts?
Why am I reading about St. Peter and St. Philip
and St. Paul?
Yeah, and if you got everything in the gospels
that you need from Jesus, you know.
Right.
And I mean, the epistles are clearly talking about,
right, the St. Paul is writing about Jesus, right?
So yeah.
but that's
Right. And so just the mere fact of the existence of acts of the apostles in the canon
says a lot about the idea of the communion of saints,
the importance of saints in their own right,
not just in how we can allegorically or otherwise get from them to Christ.
Yeah.
that God is glorified in his saints.
I mean, it does say that in Christ.
Read that somewhere.
Yeah.
Yeah, right.
And so when you see Abraham, you see Moses,
when you see these St. Paul, St. Peter,
you see the transformation of their life in Christ,
the great deeds they did in the name of Christ.
Now they preach the gospel for Christ, right?
That's... that's not...
instead of reading about Christ or instead of thinking about Christ, right? That's
something that leads you to give glory to Christ. Right? This is this is subtle play-doh
brain. Right? Why are you reading about St. Paul when you could be reading about Jesus?
Yeah. You could be reading the red letters. Why are you reading the black letters? Right?
Alright.
Ummmm.
which there's a basic illogic to what's your move past play no break.
So, we're talking about acts in particular, so that's in general, right?
That's something that acts, the existence of acts in the canon helps us see
regarding how to read narrative passages of the Bible outside of the gospels, right?
But
In terms of the book of Acts in particular,
you kind of find out the most important theme right at the beginning if you read closely.
Because St. Luke says that in his first book, Otheophilus, he wrote about all that
that Christ began to do and to teach.
And right there you have the setup for what he's trying to communicate with Acts.
That the church, particularly through her ordained leaders, but the church is and what the church
is doing on earth is the continuation of the life of Christ.
It's the continuation of Christ's deeds and it's the continuation of Christ's teaching
in the world.
Yeah, I mean, it's just simply the narrative form of referring to the church as the body
of Christ, which is not this metaphor.
You know, the church is Christ working in the world.
Right.
And that's why right from the beginning, right, what do you immediately see?
You see the 11 Apostles who are left.
of the twelve doing miracles and what miracles are they doing they're doing the same miracles
Christ did in St. Luke's Gospel.
Yeah, I mean Jesus even said that they would do greater things.
But they're always saying Christ is healed you.
Yes, yes exactly.
Exactly.
Right.
So it continues through the church.
The church is the means through which God is acting in the world.
Right.
And so...
So this then, the book of Acts also, in addition to the sort of retroactive thing we talked about
before, in terms of helping us see how we ought to read the Old Testament narratives, this also
gives us a forward, looking for how we ought to read and understand things like church history
and hagiography.
Yeah.
Right. How do we interpret the events of the Council of Nicaea?
Because I don't know if you've been on the internet.
But there's a lot of ways that gets interpreted.
Some of which have little relation to the historical facts.
Some of which are closer.
All right.
But the Bible doesn't just teach us, you know, our Protestant friends are good about
saying, well, the Bible shows us how to interpret the Bible.
And I was just making that kind of argument, right?
I was saying the book of Acts shows us something about how we ought to interpret the Old Testament.
They wouldn't be so happy with the conclusion I came to.
But they, you know, they'd have to, I think, endorse the methodology at least.
It also teaches us how to understand.
and the world and history and current events, future events, right?
How we interpret what's going on.
And the church has, frankly, always done this.
This is why we start getting people writing down church history.
Yeah. Right.
They're not just writing it down because, hey, here are some fun facts about this guy.
you may remember from the canonical book of
But she didn't know Thomas went to India, it's true. Right? That's not what people are interested in.
The reason they're interested in writing it down is what the saints are doing in every generation,
what the church is doing in every generation.
This is the record of God working in the world in each generation.
because we believe as Christians that there has never been a generation in which
God was not at work in the world.
And so good church history, real church history, the church's own history, the
church's self-understanding of history, right, is always from that
perspective, is always from the perspective of recognizing and preserving
for posterity. What God is
doing in the world at any given time in any given place, which is a very different
understanding of history than the one we get from 19th century Germany. I hope no
one ever takes a time machine back to 19th century Germany and loses it because
that we'd have a lot of angry people showing up on my Instagram.
It's been a while since you've mentioned 19th century Germans on this podcast. I guess
we're a do for it. They're going to be very well dressed. They're all going to have canes
to beat me with. So, but they're not going to be dressed with Louisiana weather. That will
be my advantage. There you go.
So the actual Apostles obviously...
And this really is obvious, right?
Or should be, does it record everything
that happened with every apostle,
even during the time period it covers?
Right.
So aside to like references to the 11
that are especially concentrated
at the beginning of the axiom apostles,
there's a whole bunch of apostles
who we never even see,
specifically singled out.
Right? Like St. Simon the Zealot. Yeah. Right? St. Martha, I'm you. Right? He's doing stuff,
right? He's preaching. He's, you know, we're kind of told generally that the 11 are doing these,
but we don't get specific details, right? Same thing with the women disciples, right? So the
Theotokos appears at the beginning of the Book of Acts. And if that's news to you,
especially to some of our Protestant listeners.
Why is that news to you? Your sole scripture, you're supposed to know these things.
Read the Bible. Get with the program.
They've talked as a few times at the beginning with other women disciples, but I mean we don't get details of like
St. Joanna, St. Mary Mangle and exactly where they went and what they were doing in the book of Acts itself.
Right. So the book of acts kind of has its own
through line just like Saint John points out that his gospel there's not enough books
of the world to write down every single thing Jesus said and did right there's not enough
books of the world to write down every single thing that every one of the apostles said
and did right. So actually the apostles is not claiming to do that actually the apostles
of being very deliberately selective.
And so the primary through line with...
the book, the acts of the Apostles, is geographic.
Christ says to the disciples, as ascension, that there
gonna be his witnesses in Judea and then Samaria and then
to the ends of the earth. Right. And so the movement of the
acts of the Apostles as a book is about the Gospel going from
Jerusalem to Rome, the capital of the Empire.
And so it follows first the 11 and the other disciples and apostles in Jerusalem, then
Saint Philip going to Samaria, and then Saint Paul going out to the ends of the earth,
right, ultimately to Rome.
And so all of these other things are going on, they're going on with the other apostles
and other things.
But we're not getting all the details in this particular...
book. And so all of that reality out there of what the other
puzzles were doing, right? It's not that that was just
instantly forgotten by everyone. Oh, well, it didn't end up in the canonical
New Testament. So I guess no one knows. Everyone just forgot.
Right? That of course is ridiculous. But sometimes you will catch people,
So we're a Protestant friends talking that way.
Right.
You know, someone in my own family said, well, the Bible doesn't say where St. Paul was buried.
So how do you know?
And my response was the Bible doesn't say where our grandparents were buried, but we both know.
right right it's not where either of us lives now either but we
know where it is. Right? And, you know, we can tell the next generation of the young relatives,
they can tell the next generation doesn't have to be the Bible. Right? So this idea that
like facts that aren't recorded in the Bible somehow instantly become unknown is kind
weird.
Right. And no one would say it about secular history. Yeah. Like who was who was the Roman
Emperor after Tiberius? I don't know. It's not in the New Testament. Yeah. And he claims
the country must be must be false. Yes. Or at least they're fallible. Right. Right. How
can you possibly know for sure it's not in the New Testament? I mean, no one would say that.
be ridiculous, right? Like.
So why is that different for a quote unquote biblical character, which is itself a term that's
a little fraught, right?
Like, no, this is an actual existing historical human being, whom the Bible mentions.
Right?
That doesn't move them into some weird category of being.
Where, you know, like the few things we know about her from the Bible, those are true.
But all the stuff about her and the Roman records, all the inscriptions he left.
left all the building brought that yeah we've got to take that with a grain of salt that's
all true. Right that really doesn't make any logical sense if you think about it very
hard for more than a couple of seconds. But the reason we're bringing that up here is
not to sort of bash on certain popular discourse from some of our Protestant friends. It's
because we're now about to talk about a bunch of tax
that are not in the New Testament.
that contain information and traditions about different apostles who do appear in the New Testament.
Those traditions, but the particular details are not in the New Testament, but we hold them to be
nonetheless true. And so, again, if you want to say to me, hey, a fact appears in the Bible,
That means 100% it's true.
I'm good with that, right? I'm good with that. But if you're going to say to me, a fact doesn't appear in the Bible, therefore it is false.
Now I'm going to be like, what? Right. Right. Right.
Right. Like so, yes, we don't have a detailed account of St. Paul's martyrdom in the New Testament. Right.
But we don't have any account of his death in the New Testament.
Does that mean he didn't die?
See what I'm saying? Right? Like we know he died. Every piece of information we have from
the ancient world says he was martyred and martyred in a certain way at a certain time
in a certain place. Why would we not believe any of it? Right? Like it just it doesn't make
sense right. We'll get it.
specific things, right, as we go through some of these.
So the first one we want to talk about is probably the most important, one of the four we're
going to talk about.
In that, it is the one that has been most broadly considered to be historically reliable.
You
So even like secular scholars, like wildly secular scholars, now basically consider the
acts of Paul that we're about to be talking about to be broad or elements of it, elements
of it I should say, to be broadly historically reliable.
Yeah, they probably wouldn't go in for the miraculous stuff.
Right, right, broadly.
And when I say that, like, there is a weird irony to it because I can think of at least one major New Testament scholar
who thinks that the, some of the stuff in the first part of the Acts of Paul is more historically reliable than he thinks major portions of the New Testament are.
So there you go, that's weird.
That's weird, but yeah.
Now there's an adj-
behind that, that'll become apparent here as we go on. But so the Acts of Paul, sometimes the whole
book gets called the Acts of Paul and Thecla. But properly speaking, there are sort of subsections of
the book, the Acts of Paul. And the first section is properly speaking the Acts of Paul and Thecla.
Yeah.
because she doesn't show up in the rest, right?
And so if you want to be technically correct,
which is the best kind of correct, then you say the book
is called the Acts of Paul.
And the first part is called the Acts of Paul and Pecla.
So as late as you see,
So you see, this is in the fourth century AD.
You see, B.S. says that at his time, there were some churches still existing, like local churches,
that considered the acts of Paul to be canonical.
Oh, so they were reading it out loud in church?
They would read from it publicly.
Yeah, you know, a reading from the acts of the Holy Puzzle Paul.
Yes.
Yeah.
So, that gives you an idea.
So when I say, right, it was broadly considered reliable.
the ancient church, like to that level. It's not just that everybody thinks, oh yeah,
that's a book to be read privately. There were people who thought it was part of the New Testament.
So since technically correct is the best kind of correct, technically speaking in some places,
at certain times this was a canonical book. Yes, because it was treated that. Yes,
yes, certain churches. Yeah. So it would be in the category of like the Deuterokan and of the Old
test of it.
where some local churches would do public greetings from those books and others would not.
Yeah.
So, uh, and state of politics,
so we're talking late second century. Yeah.
References events
that are recorded in the acts of Paul
as just events that happened.
Meaning he's not-
referencing the text, he's just referring to things as historical fact that our earliest written
account of is in the acts of Paul. Yeah. So that that gives you an idea of that's that's part of
the basis for where I say historically reliable and we'll find this with some of the other texts we
we talk about tonight too, there are other places
and people who refer to these
events that we first hear about in terms of surviving texts. We first hear about
of these books, right? But they're also attested to in these other outside places as
being just events that happen. The first and frankly only really super negative
thing. We have about the ex
of ball comes from Tertalian.
But it's not so much that he has a beef with the text as he has a beef with the existence
of St. Thackla.
I mean, it's totally and definitely had problems with women.
Yes.
To put it mildly.
He did not have a balanced view.
So specifically in the text, St. Thackla.
And as you may know, even if you've never touched
the axe of Paul in your life, especially if you're going to an antiochean church, right?
You may have just heard the life of St. Thecla, right?
Ed's stuff, right?
And not to anything about the axe of Paul, but no things about St. Thecla.
And that's where Trotolian's beef was.
St. Thecla as a disciple of St. Paul is recorded as having preached to and baptized other women.
vote.
So tell you it had a problem with the idea that a woman would be allowed to preach to
anyone or baptize anyone.
I mean, this is basically what the role of the deaconess in the early church.
Right.
If you know anything about what deaconesses actually did in the early church, right,
getting away from the present day nonsense, what deaconesses actually did in the deaconesses
Who are mentioned in the D.D.A.K. who are mentioned, right, we know existed.
in the early church, what they did was preach and teach to other women and participate in
the baptisms of other women. That's sort of exactly what they did. So, for the perspective
of the early church, there's no problem with St. Thetclad Tertullian. He left the church
for the Human Women Haters Club.
No girls allowed.
said,
said Montana's is two
profanesses that he traveled with,
but we will, you know,
hey,
we're going to be more shade there.
Less said the better.
But this text, for example,
when you're dealing with any,
with any text,
so this is a text from the early
second century.
So the early one hundreds.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
and written in the West
part of Asia Minor. And when you hear Western Asia Minor, when you're reading about ancient
texts and you're reading about this kind of stuff, Western Asia Minor, the, you should
think Ephesus.
Yeah, I mean, Western Asia Minor is kind of basically Turkey, modern Turkey, roughly.
I think I also wanted to say by the way that, you know, when you're thinking early second
century when you're talking
about that. We should remember that like the last book of the canonical New Testament is written
in what the 90s, the late, the late first century. So you're talking about the 1956 revelation.
Yeah. So this is a text that's from within just decades, just a few decades of the death of
the last apostle. Yeah.
Ephesus. So Ephesus gets destroyed later on.
Right. And that's why and essentially in terms of church polity gets replaced by Constantinople
once it's founded, right? In that part of the world as the major Christian center. But
if you read the canonical book of Acts, right, with St. Paul gives his farewell address, he gives
his farewell address to the presbyters at Ephesus. Right. Ephesus is the hub. St. John goes to Ephesus
with the Theotokos.
Say very Magdalene.
goes to Ephesus, right?
This is the, that part of the world,
Ephesus was the hub.
To the point that,
assuming you're going to an Eastern right Orthodox church,
the liturgy you celebrate,
every time you celebrate liturgy,
is a subspecies of the invasion liturgy.
Yeah, I mean, and if history had turned out
a little bit differently,
Ephesus might well have been
one of the Pentarchy or Hexarchic or whatever.
I'm sorry.
Yes. Yes. Yeah. Um, so right, that Ephesus, when you were talking about this period in history,
this is very early period in church history. Ephesus is right there with Antioch and Alexandria
and Jerusalem. Right. And Rome is still getting started. Yeah. Really. Yep. Um, they're late comers.
They're little brothers.
Anyway.
Uh...
Not sorry, Robert.
Catholic history. So, right. So, that's where it comes from. But they would have reason, as we
were just saying, they would have reason to have living memory of information about St. Paul's life.
They hadn't necessarily been written down. St. Paul's spent a lot of time in Ephesus and around
right? And so they would have access to these traditions.
to compile them and put them into a text.
But when you're looking at any texts, yeah, go ahead.
I was just gonna say, like, again, just for reference, right?
So here we are in 2026.
You know, you and I were in our, you know,
our 20s starting in the mid 90s.
Yeah.
And so I mean, mid, you know, the original mid 90s,
that's when St. John is, you know, running the apocalypse
and dying.
And then these texts are basically from like,
the equivalent of now, but, you know, 2000 years ago.
Sorry, I just want to cut it.
emphasize that for people like this is the level of closeness and time. There's a lot of living people who would have remembered some of this stuff.
Yes. Yes.
St. Paul was murdered about 50 years.
Give or take before this was written.
Right.
Okay.
So do you think that's whether that's one money python and the Holy Grail came out?
Yeah.
Well, 51 years ago.
Yeah, yeah, but so do you think if
you wanted to, you could put together a pretty good history of the year 1976, right? Just
by interviewing people who are alive at the time. Right. Obviously, yes. Right. Obviously,
this is within living memory. Right. There were still people alive who had met St. Paul
at the time. This was written. So, yeah, there's isn't some vast gulf of time for all these
these legends and weird things to grow up.
But whenever we're talking about a second century text and even an early third century text,
that's not canonical. You always end up having to answer the question, is this anostic text?
Right? Because that is a big divide in terms of non-canonical texts written during this period.
Even when we were introducing this a few minutes ago, when I was talking about the various
James literature. I said some of it's not sticking some of it's not right.
So we have to ask that question, right?
And that is at Nostek.
If the answer is yes, that gives you a pretty good explanation right off the bat about why it's not the Bible.
But in this case, and in many other cases, the answer is no.
It is not.
In fact, the text at many points is very deliberately and directly anti-nostic.
Right. So the text and, and therefore probably it seems that the major reason for writing
down these traditions, it wasn't just like, Hey, man, we got a lot of people here who
knew St. Paul and knew some interesting tidbits about him. Let's get that written down before
these people die off, right? That doesn't seem to be what occasion the right, the, the
compilation of this text. What seems to have been occasioned the compilation of this
text is actually the rise of gnosticism.
which they saw as opposed to the gospel that St. Paul had preached to them.
And so they're wanting to clearly set out.
Here's who St. Paul was, and here's what he taught over against,
right, these newfangled,
gnostic so-and-so's coming around with their nonsense.
So,
You can broadly divide the text.
of the Axe of Paul into either three or four parts.
The middle part, you can consider just to be a middle part or you consider it to be
two different things.
We'll get to that in a second.
But the first part, as we mentioned, is the Axe of Paul and Thecla.
Because St. Thecla takes up a lot of the quote unquote screen time as it were, right?
This part of the text.
And so, St. Thecala, the axiopol is not a-
only source about the existence of life of St.
Thecqua by a log shot.
So obviously there are Syrian traditions surrounding the figure of
St. Thecqua, the monastery founded at a significant place in
to get placed in our life that we'll get to here,
that we get into the text.
Feast day pilgrimages surrounding hurt right that go deeply back into Christian history.
One of the ways we know that this goes way back into Christian history is that we also
have in written form Saint Evgenia who's living in Rome.
So the other side of the empire, the other side of the
Uh, you call, you call us?
the other side of the inhabited world. In AD 185, we have talking about St.
Teclah as a role model for Christian women. Oh wow. And I mean all this just kind of underlines,
a point we've made a bunch of times, but I think it's worth reiterating is that when we look
Look at one of these texts from the early church.
These texts are not the source.
of the traditions about whoever they're talking about.
They are a witness to these traditions.
It's not like there's suddenly, this text appears out of nowhere and then suddenly people
say, oh yes, those are the things that say Paul did.
No, that doesn't make any sense.
That doesn't make any sense.
This is not historical fiction.
This is a collection of traditions being written down and this happens to be the text, the
the earliest.
text that we have that is extant because remember most everything from you know most written stuff from the ancient world is gone
most of it's gone
You know, right so this is just the earliest text that we have that bears witness to these traditions
Yes, like the the events and the traditions occur before the written stuff just like the gospels right
Jesus does all those things and then later on you get these apostles writing down
What did you do?
Yes. Yes. So St. Thecla does not come from the acts of Paul. Right. St. Thecla came from the womb of her mother into reality.
Yeah. And existed on the earth and lived and did things. That's the source. That's the original ultimate source. Right.
the information about who she is and what she did made its way
down to us, many centuries later, through various written and oral means. Right. But this
is important because the way you express it, when you say that something came from a text,
you are already applying that the text invented it. Yeah. That the text made it up. Right.
And you should even use that language.
the same reason when you're talking about the Bible, by the way. That comes from the Bible.
Well, no, that comes from reality. And the Bible is maybe, you know, the primary place for
that information was preserved for us down to the present day. But that's how it comes
from. Right, that's right. Yes, the revelation is Christ, not the
Bible, the Bible is where that revelation that came in Christ is recorded. Yeah. Very important distinction.
So, but yeah, so by 81, 85, knowledge of St. Thecla in some detail about her life
had literally made it from one end to the Roman Empire to the other, completely apart from this text.
as far as we
can tell. So yeah. Now in the text, St.
Thecla is one of St. Paul's first converts at the city of
Iconium when he goes there on his first missionary
journey. So this is kind of an overlap with the canonical
the Apostles. And she follows him.
And then she travels, which is one of the people of the several people who travels with him on his journey.
As we mentioned, she evangelizes and assists with the baptisms of women.
As St. Paul is
preaching primarily to men, once again, right?
This is the first century.
Synagogues were not
integrated.
across gender lines.
So this is what we would expect, right? This is what this is what would be normal.
Now, one of the very important things
in terms of how this text presents St. Thecla, and this will become a motif
and hagiography of particularly female saints and martyrs going forward.
is her decision to maintain her virginity, right?
Which in the ancient world and the time that she lived
was her deciding not to marry.
Yeah, which that's not a thing in the first set.
That's not a thing that women were allowed to do.
Yeah, it was just unthinkable.
Just, but within the tax she is allowed to do it
because she's making that decision.
In line with things we see St. Paul saying, it is canonical epistles so that she could devote herself to serving Christ entirely.
Devote her whole life, continue traveling with St. Paul rather than being married, staying in one place, raising children.
She wants to continue to travel, help spread the gospel, serve him, serve Christ with her whole life.
Now that may not sound that crazy to us right but...
as Father Andrew pointed out. Number one, that was a thing you were not allowed to do in the
ancient world, even in the ancient Jewish world. Women did not have that right, say, no to marriage
for that or any reason. But also the Christian embrace of that idea,
This is the beginning of the whole of the development of the whole idea.
of sexual consent as it is now come to exist in the modern world.
Yeah.
Right.
And regardless of what you think the current state of that discourse is, right?
Until right here, until the coming of Christianity, there was no such concept.
Right.
It is, it is very difficult.
to separate in ancient stories and ancient narratives,
even when you're going through the Torah and some of the commandments,
to separate consensual sexual relations from sexual assault.
So when you see the word, here goes our modernization, I'll just kill it right now.
When you see the word rape in ancient texts, like ancient Greek texts,
Right.
There are several tax famous paintings of the rape of this female character.
Rape is not a concept that had something to do with consent.
Rape was having sexual relations with someone either surreptitiously, like secretly,
like because they were married to someone else you were sneaking around,
or underfalls
pretenses. You were pretending to be a different person.
Well, and even the, I mean, even the, the English word rape within,
I mean, literally just within our lifetimes, it used to mean, I mean,
it's often had the sexual sense to it, but it used to also have a very strong
sense of just meaning to carry some, to carry, especially carry a woman off.
You know, like, so like the rape of the, yeah, the rape of the Sabine women,
was not what we would now call rape.
It was carrying them off to forcibly marry them,
but it was carrying them off.
And so they're from their father without paying the dowry.
Right, right.
I mean, I remember, and I mean, just to illustrate
that this change in English,
any ways has happened relatively recently.
There was a, the longest running off,
and see that this may be the first time,
or the first long time we've mentioned Broadway musicals,
but they're actually this off-roadway.
The longest starting off Broadway musical for a long time was a show called The Fantastices.
And in The Fantastices there was a song called Rape and it was not about sexual assault.
It was about carrying a woman off.
And but recent productions of that show no longer include that song.
And they changed yet.
In fact, now the song is called Abductions.
And they just completely different song actually.
Yeah, neuronic had even sing about it on the SNS
know, but yeah, so the idea of consent comes from this idea that comes with Christianity
in particular that women have the right to not get married in order to dedicate their
lives to serving the Lord. And so this is a, this is of, obviously, if this is sinking
this is a
massive cultural importance, right?
This is like a watershed in the development of what we think of as culture and morality
right today.
And it's something that comes from Christianity.
So, and it's why...
And then we'll move on, but it's why anybody who tells you that Christianity is misogynistic,
it acts like the pagan world loved women pre-Christianity.
You should just laugh in their face.
And why?
Yeah, it's exactly the opposite of true because they just know nothing.
Right.
Yeah.
So yeah, it might be this clip I just saw of...
Sean McDowell and friend of the show, Bart Irman, where Sean McDowell was trying to argue
that there is inbuilt into humanity this kind of basic moral compass.
Oh, and yeah, and and friend of the show, Bart Irman telling him he's full of it.
And that almost all the stuff he thought was part of the general moral compass was actually
a product of Christianity.
That was just amazing. So someone needs to build this is this is what other yeah,
barberman's new book is like virtually a sequel to Dominion.
But yeah, what are the many reasons he's friend of the show? Yeah, it's just this bizarre moment.
But
so
We also have the Acts of Paul, our earliest physical description.
I'm sure I've referenced it on the show before.
This is where it actually is in the acts of Paul.
And again, this is about circa 50 years after his death.
And we have good reason to believe that this physical
distriff is accurate for, I think, two primary reasons.
Number one, it matches our earliest iconography of St. Paul.
And number two, I think, is the most important thing
to do with the fact that we have a lot of time to do.
earliest iconography of St. Paul and number two.
it is very unflattering. So like if you were going to make up something about this figure like the
acts of Paul, they love St. Paul, they think St. Paul's great. They want you to know how great an
apostle St. Paul was and then they describe it physically and it's super unflattering. You probably
got to figure there be an honest, right? Like yeah, they could have a break otherwise. So it's to give
Keep it right.
of how unflattering they said he had really large watery eyes a very large pronounced nose
his eyebrows met in the middle. Unibrow yes he was nearly completely bald. He was a bendy
legged, meaning like bow legged and he walked awkwardly. He had big knobby knees.
Poor guy. You can imagine some of that was the result of being you know beaten and shipper
back to
all the stoned and all the things he went through. But again, and if based on these other
factors, we consider this to be broadly accurate, it makes sense of a lot of things he says
in his canonical epistles, like talking about how there was nothing about him in terms
of his physical presence, right? And rhetorical skill that would in and of itself win people
over to his cause. Right? He's not exactly an adonis.
right? This is, you know, this is not somebody who he's not he's not
Saul from the Old Testament who was a head taller than everybody else, right?
And like, yeah, strapping and, you know, everyone wants him to be king.
Saul of Tarsus was kind of the other end of the physical spectrum.
And so, but that again shows you it's his message.
It's what he's saying, it's what he's preaching, right?
That is important.
right, and that was captivating people. We then get the story of St.
necklace suitors who given that she wasn't allowed to say no in the ancient
world didn't want to take no for an answer in terms of marrying her. And so
Chaser to a large rock which rock opened up in front of her and hit her
in an area with a spring of water.
And you can still go there.
Cap safe.
And that is Mouloula.
Yeah.
Maloula, father.
Maloula.
Yeah, okay.
Take your accent.
That's why I said.
I've just said,
I'm a white boy.
I don't have that accent.
Well, I am also white.
But I did marry into a vast Middle Eastern world.
So that's it.
Yeah
go there it's it's serious. I'm not saying it's an affectation I'm just saying you know
it's not something I do. It's an adaptation. So uh the uh right yeah so that that is uh still there
still a place that you could go. Yeah. And then the last bit and this is not exactly historical fiction
but it's not
It's definitely not historical fact in the modern sense either.
The last bit of the first part of the Axel Paul tells a story that is very clearly borrowed.
It's a story that everyone at the time, everyone at the early second century had heard before.
Probably a lot of our listeners have heard before, even if they've never read the Axel Paul.
is, uh, St. Paul meets a lion.
And this lion has an injured paw.
Yeah.
It's making him upset.
So St. Paul helps him with the injured paw,
helps him out, heals him.
That preaches the gospel to him and baptizes the lion.
There's a, there's a twist.
As one does.
Right.
and there they go.
separate ways and then later on St. Paul gets thrown to the lions for preaching the
Gospels and guess who one of the lions turns out to be? It's the Christian lion. It's the Christian
lion. Yeah. Unfortunately for St. Paul that doesn't mean he just blesses his meal. He
He refrains from eating St. Paul, being a Christian lion.
It's sort of like that scene from Thor Ragnarok with the Hulk.
But so he does it now.
Those of you with a little bit of even a little bit of classical education may
recognize the story of Andrew Clees of the lion.
Yeah.
Like pretty instantly.
Uh, and you're not wrong.
Right.
You're not wrong.
So this is taking a story that would have been very, this is not plagiarism
because all of the original readers would be familiar with this story.
Yeah. Right. So I mean, this would be like if I was writing a story and I insert into the story I'm writing that the main character gets bitten by a radioactive spider and can now stick to walls. Okay.
I know everybody has heard of spider-man, right?
Like, I was trying to allude to spider-man, that was the whole point, right?
I was...
making a Spider-Man reference.
So this is the text making an Andrew Cleese
of the Lied reference.
Yeah.
And so when you see something like this,
when you see a sub-reference,
now I feel like I'm telling people
how to interpret the things I say.
But anyway, when you hear a sub-reference,
and it's not on family guy because family guy is lame.
I said it. It's lame. It's always been lame.
There are subreferences go nowhere, right?
Like it's manatees. We've known this.
So, what someone makes a subreference,
where there's intertextuality like this,
the first thing you want to look at is not
what is the thing be referenced or what are the things in common.
That's the mistake.
Oh, look, this is just Andrew Clees of the Lion.
Look, yeah, forget about it.
about it.
I mean, I was just saying, and I mean, I don't, I'm not saying, you know, making
execution of bad faith here, but also like the person in the chat who said, wait, can
the church still baptize animals? I'm like, no, that's, no, that's not what this story
is about.
Yeah.
We'll get there.
It's a little too bad.
Yes.
Oh, yeah.
No, I already said this to you, Father Andrew. Like, don't do not take this whole, the
wrong way guys
I do not need a line 35 deep of middle age women in their cats looking for baptisms at
the church tomorrow.
Although as another person pointed out of the chat, trying to baptize a cat would be
pretty exciting.
Oh, no, I do not need that.
The blood.
You can't have that much blood in the church, right?
So yeah, you would never immerse a cat three times.
One maybe if you surprised it, but then you're done.
Like
I mean first you have to put them in a sack and then you know sorry wow you took it again
taking it to a dark place first the horrors of the Second World War now you're drowning cats
like what has happened during this move father Andrew who hurt you I've finally snapped after all
these years of talking to you man. You're gonna turn it to be. Yeah. So
Yeah, so you want to look for the differences, right?
And the main difference, as people have correctly noted,
is St. Paul here, preaches to,
preaches the gospel to it that baptizes the lion,
which obviously that part doesn't happen
in Andrew Cleese and the lion.
Okay.
Right.
So the overarching structure of Andrew Cleese and the lion
has been borrowed.
order to send us a message about the salvation, the idea that salvation, the salvation that comes in Christ,
extends not just to humans, but to the whole of creation. And why addocles of the line? Well,
Orion is a wild animal. It is an unclean animal. It is a non-domesticated animal.
a fierce animal, but potentially will eat a person.
Right?
And so it is sort of an element of the created order that is perhaps the most hostile to man.
But God's love, His saving love, extends even to, right, that creature, that part of the created order.
Huh?
Now!
Again, this doesn't mean we're going to go around baptizing animals.
Right.
Uh, if you want to go and preach the gospel to a herd of sheep or cows, uh, go ahead.
It works really well.
Take it from a Dutchman.
It works really well with cows.
They will just stay there and stare at you while you preach for hours in a time.
Uh, same sometimes happens in Dutch churches, but that's a whole other, whole other thing.
Um,
But what's the
point then if the text isn't telling us we should go baptized animals. What's the point of having this like a baptized? It's a point to argue this. Well, who would you be arguing that against in the early part of the second century?
You be arguing that against various Gnostic sects.
Because what is one of the basic beliefs of a sect that would cause us to identify it as
it's that the created order is
itself in some way evil. Yeah, or needs to be transcended or something. Right. Is evil,
and so you're saved out of it, you're saved from it. Okay. And so again, we have a lion, a creature
that is hostile to humanity. Right. So if you're going to peg something as evil, if you're going to
talk about even just nature, red, and tooth, and claw, right? Even that level of evil. Right.
Allions are pretty good symbol for that.
Right? Yeah.
And so the text is here using this is using this borrowed
partially borrowed narrative element to communicate to us, right, that
the whole created order finds its salvation in Christ and
through the gospel of Jesus Christ
even the parts that may seem the most hostile to humanity are not actually evil
even if they are part of God's creation.
I mean, God said that it was good.
Yes.
And now, you may think, okay, well, yeah, but you're just importing this whole anti-nostic thing in.
But that now brings us to section two of the Axe of Paul.
And section two, or possibly two and three, if you want to divide these,
Section 2 is made up of two letters, two epistles.
that aren't canonical epistles of St. Paul, but two epistles, and the subject of these
two epistles is narcissism. So that's literally where the narrative segues into the letters
about narcissism. So, you know, I think it's pretty fair, right, contextually, to see
the connection there. Now these two letters are not two letters from
Saint Paul. One of them is a letter to Saint Paul from the church at Corinth. That's the first one.
And then the second one is Saint Paul's response back to the church at Corinth.
And someone may think, well wait, if you know anything about, if you've read recently first and
second Corinthians, you know that there were other letters, that there was at least one letter
that St. Paul sent to Corinth.
before 1 Corinthians, that there was probably one in between, right?
You know that there are these sort of quote unquote missing letters of Saint Paul the Corinth.
Saint Paul also refers to letters he had received from them.
So you might think, oh, are these two letters in the acts of Paul,
two of those letters that are missing for the New Testament?
Answer no.
There and it's not just me saying no, they're not presented as that.
They're presented.
This is just, this is a separate mail exchange.
This is a separate email thread from the canonical epistles, right?
This is a whole separate set of correspondence.
That's how it's presented in the acts of Paul.
So the acts of Paul is not claiming that these fit back in between the canonical epistles.
The acts of Paul is presenting these as a second follow up thing, okay?
And so...
the first letter, the letter from Corinth, basically they lay out the problem. The problem
is these two wandering presimeters have shown up, not that anything like this would ever happen
today. They've shown up, they're preaching some kind of weird sounding stuff, right? That
sounds like it contradicts the stuff that St. Paul had taught them. And so they're asking
You can see Paul.
Hey, here's the stuff they're teaching.
Is this right?
Should we receive them?
Should we let them preach this stuff?
Or should we throw them out?
Right.
And call them anathema.
And the two main things that the letter says that they're teaching
is number one, that the cosmos, right?
The world, the cosmos, is evil.
It was...
created by lesser angels not by God.
So there's one big,
Gnostic red flag,
right,
and Ceeves related to Marcianism
that would have been going around at this time, right?
Old Testament God is a lesser God, right?
Creator created the evil creation
or at least bad creation.
They've got a platonic metaphysics.
So lesser means bad, right?
lesser being evil.
in that kind of mesophysics.
And then there could be out after strike two.
Strike two is they're teaching that Jesus was not
actually incarnate as flesh and blood.
And this of course is related because flesh and blood,
the material creation is medieval.
Yeah, if you're a, if you're a gnostic,
you don't believe in the incarnation, that would be crazy.
Right.
defeat the whole purpose, right? Us being you and I being incarnate is the problem
according to dostics. So as one might anticipate, St. Paul sends his letter back to Corinth saying,
no, these guys are anathema, throw them out, have nothing to do with them.
So, pop of what upside the head for me.
That last one, not litter.
literally. But have nothing to do with them, right? Throw them out. So this is what we
meant. We said the text is clearly anti-nostic and this is sort of introduced by the episode
with the lion. So after these two letters, the last part of the acts of Paul is the martyrdom
of St. Paul.
St. Paul goes to Rome.
He stands trial before near.
And Nero has a cupbearer, a servant who says, good friend, their close pals, named Patrickless.
Okay.
If you have a classical education, who was it, Killy's close pal and really good friend?
Patricleist falls over dead.
You're going to get the idea from these non-canonical acts we read tonight that people are really fragile
in the second century.
It does not take a lot to kill a person in the second century.
But Patricleist falls over dead.
St. Paul, right, works America raises Patricleist from the dead, intending to use this as an opportunity
to now preach.
the gospel to Nero and try to convert him to Christianity. Nero however is just scared.
Right? Nero sees this Saint Paul raise a guy for the dead and is like, oh no, he's going to use
his magic powers to overthrow me and take over the empire. I need to kill this guy.
And so Nero begins his persecution of Christians and he
orders, St. Paul beheaded and in the telling of the acts of Paul, when St. Paul's head is
severed, the stome of his neck pours out milk instead of blood.
That's wild.
Yes.
The idea here is that this is milk and this is a reference back.
to his teachings. Yeah, yeah, that even his death is nourishing. Yes, sort of thing. Yeah, yeah.
Yeah. That's the idea of the symbolism. There are other traditions and other places about the
details, say Paul Stett, everywhere he's beheaded, he's beheaded under Nero. Beheading is how you
were executed if you were a Roman citizen. Roman citizens could not be crucified.
Chris Eviction was
considered barbaric and horrible. That's why they only did it to barbarians and known persona
slaves, etc. So St. Paul as a Roman citizen, the right to be beheaded instead, which was considered a
mercy, there is a church in Rome where this happened that you could go to to this day. St. Paul's relics
Thanks.
turned near their St. Paul's relics have relatively recently, then they ran all the scientific
tasks. Now, you can't prove that something that this is St. Paul, right? It's not like
we have a St. Paul D&A record to compare it to, but that did demonstrate that it was a
first century Jewish man who had been beheaded buried there. And that he was wearing first
century Palestinian.
textiles. Well, who could that possibly be? Yes, yes. So it's
confirmed as far as you can confirm it. So the detail of the
milk, right, is the main thing that's ascribable to the text
in particular. And that's an interpretation, right? That's a
symbolic interpretation of St. Paul's death, that is telling us
something about St. Paul's death.
That St. Paul was beheaded under Nero is a very firmly established
active history.
Yeah.
So yes, so that's where the acts of Paul ends.
All right.
Well, we are just getting started.
Really crazy stuff is yet to come.
Yeah, it's a come yet to come.
So that wraps up the first half of this episode of Laura Spears podcast.
And we'll be right back after this short break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and father Stephen DeYoung
We'll be back in a moment.
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient Near Eastern texts such as the Bale Cycle
portray the pagan god Bale as a rebel.
The hero of a revolution worshiped and glorified
for his long string of victories.
in the bail flow.
a biography of the devil. Father Stephen the Young shows that the Hebrew
scriptures consciously turn the Bale story on its head. Depicting him as a
failed and defeated rebel who nonetheless tries to steal the glory that
belongs to Almighty God. From these scriptures the figure of the devil emerged
within Jewish and Christian tradition. Father Stephen works through the old and
New Testament passages that referred to various Bale stories and he surveys
Bale worship through followers beliefs, religious practices, and liturgical
to show that the figures of bail and
in the devil, the Prince of demons are one in the same.
You can find the bailbook at store.agentfaith.com.
That's store.agentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF.
Radio. Hey welcome back everybody it's the second half of this episode on
should I say uncannotical non-canonical extra canonical. Sub-canonical. Super.
Super uncannotical. Metaconical. Text about the Apostles. Books to be read in the
church parking lot.
There he go.
Yes.
Only readable in the narthex.
So the ex
So North Texas.
I'm not sure if that was a commercial break or a visit to a Belgian disco tech.
And that was the voice of Simon everybody.
By the way, yeah, yeah, I like it.
I really like Simon's drawings.
Nice.
That's back his name.
Yes.
So anyway, yeah.
So we talked about the acts of Paul, which also of course includes a subsection of that
that is the ex of C Paul and C. Thecla.
C. Thec-
the proto-marter among women, super beloved in the Antioch in church but
universally beloved throughout the Orthodox Church but like we double quadruple
triple you know a hex stupel down on our veneration of of St.
Thessalon and the Antioch in church. She's she's like a fifth class saint on the
Russian calendar. Really? Yes she's like the third or fourth one listed on that day.
Russian brothers and sisters sit.
down for a moment. Yeah. Yeah.
We have a talk. She doesn't
align yourself with the chair of St. Peter in
Antioch. That's right. That's right.
The successor of Peter, you guys. Um, speaking of Peter.
Yes, that was a good, good, uh, good segue.
We haven't actually gotten any on topic phone calls yet. So, uh, yeah.
And no one goes here's about on topic.
And no one said-
the secret word either. So, oh, yeah. Yeah. If you want to call it about baptizing cats,
like we can, I mean, that's true. We can go there. I will baptize that movie. There
was some dude in the chat who wanted to, who wanted to debate, you know, he wanted to
tell us the trinitarian theology was false. So he had to be put in time out. But anyway.
Well, I thought someone would call since we...
I made that big, that big pitch there, but I guess Mike has just taken the evening off.
I don't know.
That could be two.
Yep.
All right.
Well, St. Paul, not that many questions about St. Paul.
That's a lot.
Don't worry.
We'll give you stuff to talk about this half.
How about that?
How about that brother of St. Andrew, everybody?
He's interesting.
St. Andrew's little bro.
Yeah.
That's right.
Did you notice that the icon that I picked for this, this episode?
St. Andrew is right in the middle.
People are just going to just
going to take you one of those
one of those EP papalists.
That's what they're going to.
No, no, no.
You're trying to.
That's all legend.
Okay.
Anyway, so, uh, yes.
So now we're going to turn to the
acts of Peter.
Uh, and, uh, St. Peter slightly
important figure in the early
Church.
Indeed.
He
Looks for a hot minute like he might be the main character of the acts of the Apostles
and if you were the sort of person who thought that St. Peter was just taking over for Jesus after the end of the gospel of St. Luke
You'd expect him to be the main character for the whole book of the acts of the Apostles even though he isn't
But he sort of.
you know, as you know, if you've actually read the Acts of the Apostles, he kind of frankly disappears.
Right. Basically not very vicar Christi is he? Yeah, he, he disappears. He pops up again at the
Council of Jerusalem in Acts 15, which he doesn't share and doesn't issue the final statement on.
I mean, we love St. Peter, but submits himself to the Council. And then, and it's authority.
But then he sort of disappears again for the rest of the book of Acts.
So the Acts of Peter, we know for a bunch of things,
including his epistles that he goes to Rome.
And so the Acts of Peter is a text that collects some very early traditions
about St. Peter.
from Rome and its environs, the Christian communities that church is there.
So St. Fodius, the great, actually believed that the Acts of Paul and the Acts of Peter had the same author
when he did his catalog of the library at Constantinople, which is a thing he did
that maybe people don't know about.
But we now don't think that's the case.
We can see what he was looking at.
Right.
So he was just looking at the two texts and the Greek and that kind of thing is very similar.
So he was going based on the style and kind of the syntax.
Yeah.
But it's now clear based on some other things we have more manuscripts from different places,
some different things.
that in a different languages that the Axif Peter was written later in the second century.
So it's not impossible that whoever compiled the Axif Paul
50 years later also compiled the Axif Peter, that's not impossible. But it seems less likely
than that there is a second author. So as we said, this is a compilation
of traditions about Saint Peter,
a number of the traditions that are recorded here,
particularly surrounding his death.
We have other independent sources
with basically the same information.
This is we did with the Acts of Paul.
Acts of Peter was incredibly popular as a text
in the ancient church,
because we have multiple copies
in sort of all of the major languages.
right, that you would have this stuff in.
So it's originally in Greek, but we've also got Latin,
Coptic, Armenian, Ethiopic, Syriac, right, just across the board,
multiple copies, all these different translations,
all these different languages.
That's part of what lets us kind of hone in on better on exactly
when it was written and when these translations were made.
Because we're not just working from one version of the text or what copy.
Um.
As we mentioned, any text from the second century, even though this is later in the second
century, any text from the second century, you got to ask, is it Gnostic?
Answer is no because it is very clearly anti-Gnostic.
We will see as we saw with the Acts of Paul, it is not ambivalent in any way about Gnosticism.
And Nostisism is actually represented.
by a figure in the narrative, that figure being Simon Magus, who will talk about more here in a couple of minutes.
So it begins, the acts of Peter begins with St. Peter arriving in Rome.
He travels there with his family, with his wife, and kids who are alluded to within the canonical New Testament.
So at first, 20 is...
verse 5, remember St. Paul says that he would have the right to take a wife and children with him in his travels the way
Seifas and the other apostles did so he specifically mentioned St. Peter as having a wife and children and traveling with them
And of course famously in
St. Luke's Gospel chapter 4 verses 38 through 40
Christ healed St. Peter's mother-in-law, which kind of requires you to-
have a wife, right? Insert old school mother-in-law joke here about how she's a real battle axe or something similar.
But that old, any young man material and buddy hack it, we got it, we got to bring some of that stuff back.
So the next speaker begins with...
them arriving in Rome and then we get this episode, which one of the themes you've probably
gleaned already denied and that you're going to continue to glean is that when people interpret
these texts, people tend to interpret them with weird agendas. So here's what happens in the text,
then we'll talk about interpreting it.
So what happens if the text is...
Roman guy, Roman pagan guy wants to marry St. Peter's daughter.
Okay.
St. Peter doesn't want her to get married.
So he prays that God will paralyze her.
He prays, God paralyzes his daughter.
Roman pagan dude says, nah.
Yeah.
I don't like Mary.
She's damaged.
paralyzed woman. So he moves on, say, Peter prays again, God cures her paralysis.
So that's what happens in the text. Most modern scholarly interpreters you find will use
this episode as evidence that I'm not joking or exaggerating. That early Christians hated
sex and thought it was evil.
I mean, I mean, just think about the layers of that even besides from what I know you're
about to say, which is like, here's a guy who's married.
Right.
Say Peter is married.
Not into clerical celibacy.
And as children, so he has children.
Right.
Like even just that by itself.
Yeah.
Yes.
Right?
But also, so see you can see from this that Christians would rather see their children be crippled
and get married and have sexual relations.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, what are the details that they're leaving out that you get if you read the Acts of Peter
closely?
Well, here's the first...
important detail. Say, Peter's daughter is 10. Huh? That kind of changes a picture just a
little bit. 10 years old. Which I mean, you know, not to not to play devil's advocate for the
Romans, but Romans would have had no problem with that. Right. So if you understand the social
setting at the time, say Peter is not a Roman citizen.
Nor is his daughter, meaning a Roman man could take a 10 year old Jewish girl as a sex slave anytime he wanted to.
Yeah.
Okay.
So what's a Peter here is trying to prevent is not his daughter settling down with a nice man and having a family.
He's trying to prevent her being trafficked.
Underage sex slavery, especially with a pagan Roman. Yes, with a pagan Roman.
Well, a Christian Roman would think would not be so much.
No.
Into the underage sex library.
Um, what would hope at least?
Um, right?
And so, societally, St. Peter had no means to prevent this.
You couldn't go to a court.
You're like your honor.
I don't want him to take my 10-year-old daughter.
Yeah, I mean who say Peter say Peter is not
even like St. Paul, he's not a Roman citizen. He's literally non-persona as far as the
Romans are concerned. Yes. Yes. So him praying and having something happen to his daughter
that caused the Roman to lose interest and move on, that's the only way St. Peter has
to prevent this horrible thing from happening. Okay. And yes, the language is used in his
prayer that St. Peter wants to preserve her from sin. That's not the sin of getting
married and having kids.
Quotan Quotan.
Right.
Like that's a sin.
It's the sin of her being like defiled by a pagan Roman adult when she's 10.
Yeah.
He wants that not to happen to his daughter, which I mean, that's just called good parenting.
Yes, that's called being a dad.
Okay.
Like, yeah.
So, yes.
Right.
So, and the reason I'm spending
time on this, right, is I know we like headlines, okay? You know how I know we like headlines?
Because I've made a mistake a few times in my life of reading YouTube comments. And so I've
seen all of you commenting on videos with me and them. And by that I mean commenting on the title
of videos with me and them. Yeah, right. We like headlines, okay? Right? It's the cardinal
sin of the internet. People commenting without reading or listening or watching. But most people aren't
gonna ever
even people into this show, I know most of the people who listen to this will probably
never sit down and read the acts of Peter in full. Okay. So if anybody knows anything about
the acts of Peter, if anybody knows anything about these texts, it's usually from some documentary
they watched. Yeah. Which often sound about this in the documentary is going to be somebody with
PhD after their name saying, we know from this the Christians thought sex was a
the nightly evil.
Yeah.
Right.
You're going to accept their summary of it without investigating.
We have to do that.
We can't investigate everything.
No one has enough time to study everything they're told in detail to verify every single
thing.
No one can do that.
So we end up just accepting a lot of this stuff.
But when it comes to...
matters of spiritual importance by the teachings of Christianity and stuff. You can't just accept these sound lights.
Right, you can't just accept these characterizations because you don't have to push very hard. You only have to read enough to find out that his daughter is 10 and you kind of know that their whole narrative falls apart.
Right. Like that's something else is going on here. Right.
So, yes.
So that is the story of through St. Peter's prayers, God rescuing his daughter from being horribly violated by a pagan Roman.
Okay. Good job, Peter.
Yes.
Right.
And thank you, God, right, for doing that.
Okay.
So
After this, we get a little more into the meat of St. Peter's Day in Rome and his rivalry
with Simon Magus, who we mentioned.
So Simon Magus, yeah.
I was just saying, dun dun dun.
Oh, okay.
Yes, the official.
Simon Magus, of course, shows up in the canonical acts of the Apostles, tries to pay for the
ability to bestow the Holy Spirit. Yeah, disciples.
original the simony. Magus is not his last name. It's the idea that he's a
sorcerer. Mage involved in magical practices, pagan magical practices of the
day. So as he appears here in Rome, he has not learned his lesson. So Simon
Magus is here. The text presented as sort of the archetype of
We know historically
that narcissism was made up of a bunch of different cults and groups and sects.
Different parts of the world that had their own origins, but like Simon Megas is here,
he's the figure who represents all of them within this narrative.
If we could kind of, we've combined several historical characters into this one character
for the sake of narrative.
And so...
St. Peter is traveling around in Rome. He's doing miracles. He's baptizing people, making them Christians, right?
The church is growing. At the same time Simon Magus is traveling around in Rome and he's using a
combination of sorcery and fakery, not in the faqueer Hindu religion sense, but in the
the slide of hand bogus sense to
begin sort of effectively a cult that is
Nostasis, right, a Nostic cult. And this culminates in
St. Peter and Simon Magus are going to sort of have a
wizard duel. And by wizard duel, I mean, it's
deliberately evoking like Moses and the sorcerers
or the wizards in, or magicians in Pharaoh's court,
right, like Janice and Jambras. We're going to have
this showdown between St. Peter and Simon Magus
and Simon Mac.
and Simon Magus, sort of for his ultimate trick when he decides to pull out all the stops.
He takes off into the air and he's flying around over the city of Rome.
Right?
You'll believe a man can fly, right?
So he's doing that stick to show his powers and St. Peter prays and Simon Magus crash
and burns and gets mangled.
Yeah, it literally describes him getting
like a whole bunch of pagan Roman doctors run over and they're all trying to save his life and fix him but no he's he's wrecked
St. Peter wins flawless victory
So then after that comes one of the most
famous
Traditions about St. Peter
That there is
outside of
I'm sorry.
outside of the text of the New Testament, which we have tested, which we have tested
on to a whole bunch of other places as well as the acts of Peter.
And that is what is often called the whole Quovatus story or the Quovatus incident.
St. Peter hears that Nero's persecution is beginning, those people who he's been preaching
2 and baptizing 2 are starting to be persecute.
and so St. Peter gets ready. You know, they come to him and tell him, oh, this is happening.
St. Peter, you're one of the leaders. They're going to be after you. You got to get out of here.
So he packs up and he starts to leave. And as he's leaving Rome on the road, he sees Christ
carrying his cross going the other way, going back into the city.
And St. Peter says to him famously, Dominic Quovatus, Lord, where are you going?
And
and Christ says that he is going to be crucified again in the city of Rome.
And St. Peter sort of realizes if he leaves during this persecution, if he goes and he hides, he'll be doing it again.
He'll be repeating his denial of Christ.
And so he can't do that. He turns around. He goes back into the city.
He stays with his people
the persecution, he ends up getting arrested, he ends up getting crucified and he gets crucified
famously upside down, inverted, which is why the St. Peter Cross looks like a regular cross,
but just upside down. Yeah. So and that is not historically odd actually. The Romans, especially
Roman centurions were real...
sickos, like literally, they would get bored. And so they would crucify people in what they
thought were interesting ways all the time. Upside down, sideways, backwards, right, just
to kind of amuse themselves because they were bored at killing all these people. And sometimes
the Romans would crucify hundreds of people at a time, like Derek Spartacus's rebellion and
stuff. So, you know.
horrible torture and murder, I guess gets dull after the 150th time. So they would do things like this.
So and the fact of St. Peter's death in Rome by crucifixion and even some of the other details is
testified to by St. Clement, St. Ignatius of Antioxane, Aranneus, Tertolian, UCBS, a whole bunch of other
independent accounts, right? So the source of that.
fact is not the acts of Peter. In fact, since we told you the acts of
Peter is written toward the end of the second century, several of those figures,
like St. Clement St. Ignatius St.
Hernandez are writing before that. Yeah. Right. So this is just a known thing.
And of course, there is the illusion within St.
John's gospel about St. Peter stretching out his arms going where he does not
want to go there.
that being a reference to the manner of his death. So, you know, it's real
special pleading to try and argue that this didn't happen. Sorry, Protestant
friends who are inclined to make that argument. You're trying to ice skate uphill.
That's all I'm saying.
So much for the acts of Peter.
Do you have any acts of Peter calls?
I don't know.
Either, either one is either enthralled or just dumbfounded.
So dumbfounded board detiers.
I don't know.
That could be it too.
Old hat.
Okay.
Well, I heard people were getting bored, so now we're up in the ante.
We're going all in.
All right.
Whatever you think of this next one, it ain't boring, my friend.
And any hopes that monetizing is going to be a good thing.
hopes that monetize.
out this video are gone. By the time we're done with the acts of John, oh boy, that is riding to that.
It's pretty impressive. Nice. So the acts of John,
addition to being just a wild ride, as we'll see, becomes important in large part due to the
it becoming a point of argumentation in these
seven technical counsel.
You may not have seen that coming,
unless you're Michael Gart, in which case you saw it coming.
So we'll come back to what's we're done talking about,
what's in the text.
We'll come back to the seven technical counsel
and why it became important there.
But so like the other ones we've been talking about,
Right?
the act of John is a collection of
St. John traditions.
It is a text from the mid
second century.
So in between the acts of
follow the acts of Peter around
circle 150 AD.
You get the acts of John.
Right.
St. Justin Martin is writing.
Yes.
You get the original composition of the acts of John.
We're going to talk about that in a second.
And so that means that, and it's also from Western Asia Minor,
code for emphasis, where Satan John was also active.
Yeah, right.
We're also talking about within about 50 years of St. John's death.
So these are like his spiritual grandchildren are the ones who
or recording these traditions.
Do you think somebody's grandchildren
are kind of a reliable witness to stories
about their grandparents?
In general, yes.
In general, I would say yes.
So there is the original text in Greek.
And then there's a chunk of text
that gets inserted into the text.
So how do they know that?
How do they know that this is it a rag?
different styles? Is it because the content? They don't. We're just guessing. No. So,
no, we know that for a whole bunch of reasons, for a whole bunch of reasons. So the writing style
is completely different. The vocabulary is completely different in this added section. It's a different
genre. Yeah. Right. So up until this addition, this added section begins, it's like narrative,
of telling us these stories.
in St. John's life. And then all of a sudden, at the beginning of what's now chapter 87,
right, St. John just kind of like turns toward camera like Jim on the office and
shrug starts talking to the reader. Oh, that's fun. Right. And he does that until the end of
chapter 105 and then it goes back to third person narrative. Yeah. So you get this weird
like address to the
reader, it's got a completely different vocabulary, it's got a completely different Greek style
for much later. And the theology in it is cookie. Such that, so we know that there was
There was a version of the Acts of John that was used by the Manakis.
And suspiciously the weird
theology of this inserted chunk kind of matches theirs. So to give you a couple of examples.
Did this address to the reader? The Manakis was the weird, heretical group that
St. Augustine belonged to before it became a Christian. Yes. Yes. That's probably the
the touching point that most people would have in their heads. Oh yeah. Yeah. Maybe we'll do an
episode someday about the mannequies.
fascinating stuff. They have three
Christs, only one of whom is Jesus of
Nazareth. But so in this weird inserted
address for the reader, St. John says,
hey, you know, sometimes we tried to
touch Jesus and he was tangible and
you could touch him and then other times
our hands would just pass right through
him. Aproposal nothing. Let me just
Yeah, I was really...
Isn't it the apostle that we have lead on his breast?
Yeah, he would be funny if he said he fell over.
Right? Like if we just went to prop comedy with the Nazis.
Right.
And he also, he retells the story of the Transfiguration.
And he leaves out the whole thing with Moses and Elijah being there.
Yeah.
You're going to go, huh, do you not like the old testament for some reason?
Little sus, right?
Yeah.
So for all those reasons, it's pretty clear that this is an insertion, right?
Syntax doesn't match, vocab doesn't match, genre doesn't match, theology doesn't match,
right?
Like, there's the content.
We know a group with that weird theology.
was using a version of the text centuries after it was written. By the way, speaking of
texts, that's something good segue. But yes, speaking of a part of text from a mannequin.
I know, no, no, no. We actually have a caller who has a question about some of this stuff.
So, so yeah, let's just put them on through. So Paul, welcome, Laura Spiris podcast.
Chris is risen.
He's risen indeed.
Thank you very much for having me, Father.
Yeah, he's just phone call technically what of the acts of Paul
Lester lesser Paul, but sure
This is this is a Paul in Texas
So I wanted to ask I don't have any particular questions based on what y'all covered so far and I wanted to tell y'all that maybe it's because
Maybe a bunch of the listeners tonight are like me where they just don't know enough about this to even like have a question yet
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
I had nothing prepared because I don't have nothing there is any defect yet.
But I do have a question in relation to a pocket fund in general but like this would include
the old test and stuff.
So, I was orthodox for three years thank God on Holy Saturday and in the entire time,
it's only really in the Lord of Spirit kind of online community that I've seen like a general
kind of affinity for the apocryphal text.
whereas in the standard Orthodox world
that I've encountered thus far,
that it still seems that there's some kind of like
what's the word I'm looking for, aversion to it.
I wanted to ask what the reason for that is
because some of the people I've heard talk about it,
particularly in regards to the book of Enoch,
it seems like it's more than just like, you know,
convertitis or something like a holdout
that we brought over from the Protestant world
And it seems like...
there are some people that think that the patristic teaching on a lot of these
sex is it's better to stay away as opposed to just reading and bribe it.
Yeah. And I'm confused by that.
Well, I mean, the first thing that I'll say is I, I'm not just trying to sell a book here.
It was written for this purpose.
I do recommend Father Stevens book, which is called apocrypha, which, which treats a
lot of this stuff in detail and gives a framework for understanding it.
But I think
Here's the thing, a lot of what's in these texts is in the church.
It's in the saints lives.
It's in our hymns.
Right?
It's, it's, it's, it's, it's simply is digested, right?
Without, largely without pointing out a text, it's, it's the same content in many cases
that's being represented.
So I, I do think honestly, in some cases, I do think it is
is a kind of culturally Protestant attitude.
And here's why.
Like one of the things that Father Stephen puts
in that book is, you know, when he, you know,
and correct me if I'm wrong about this father,
but I mean, like when you were picking your table of contents,
like which books you were gonna,
which texts you were gonna talk about.
Father Stephen chose St. Nikki Foto's
Petric of Constant Snowball, his list of books
that he said are profitable to read,
but are not considered.
canonical texts. There was not read aloud as scripture in church. So this is a patriarch
of Constantinople and a saint who says this. And it's like almost a millennium later. I
can't remember when this when a saint Niki Poros is the ninth century father, 10th beginning
of the ninth century, so this is, you know, this is like triumph of Orthodoxy era, right?
You know, roughly the time.
when we the the events that gets celebrated on Sunday of Orthodoxy which happen in 843 as I recall. So that same era
right and so he is pointing and saying yeah these are good books to read
we don't they're not Bible but they're good books to read you know in a certain context
right so I think part of it is just that
English speaking Orthodox Christianity and I mean I don't know what other languages you read or understand Paul
but English speaking Orthodox.
Christianity is still kind of appropriating consciously talking about the whole Orthodox
tradition.
If that makes sense.
But like I said, I mean, these things are, they're in the texts of our, our, our liturgical
hymns.
A lot of these same traditions are in the lives of saints.
Like we just said, for instance, Saint Peter is crucified upside down.
If you've ever read the Life of St. Peter, that's always mentioned.
whatever version of the life that you read.
So, or like, you know, the traditions that we have about St.
Thetkla, this is the big witness that we have to those traditions.
It's not the only one, but it's the big one.
St. Thetkla is a saint to the church.
She celebrated it September 24th.
Her a politician references her learning from St. Paul.
Like, this is all there. It's all represented there.
It's just that most of the time when you're doing catacasus, your
priest is probably not going to say, and now let's read the Acts of Paul and
Thecla. It's just, you know, if you talk about Saint
Thecla, what's known about her life will be mentioned. And it just so happens.
It's the same stuff that's in that text. So that's my take on. I mean, I don't
know. Father, did you want to add some track, multiply, divide anything?
Yeah. Well, so I think there's broadly two main arguments against
considering this stuff. So this, this stuff in arguably is Father Andrew
it's part of our tradition.
Right. Like we did an episode on the testimony of the 12 patriarchs. I mean, that's preserved
at Mount Athos. Right. Like, yeah, it's incontrovertible that this is part of our Orthodox tradition.
Okay. But so in terms of how much emphasis it receives, I think there's a good argument
and a bad argument. Right. Now, I want to be fair and give both. Okay. The argument that
I think is fair.
And this argument you might hear from
other person who hosts a show about the scriptures on ancient faith, right?
Who I think has a little bit of an issue with how much we talk.
We talk about this stuff a lot less than people think on Lord of
Serenets, but, like, there's a bunch of people out there.
There's a whole meme out there that all we ever talk about is the book of
Enic on this show.
We have literally never done an episode on the book of Enic.
All we talk about, right?
But, but, but the person in question who's an ancient faith host, I think,
would say it I think.
kind of has said that, you know, most Orthodox people don't know the actual canonical scriptures
well enough to be moving on to this other stuff, right? And I think that's fair in some
ways. I'm saying that kind of thing is fair, right? Because our Orthodox Church is huge.
There is no human who comprehends all of it. Yeah. There is no human out there who is equally
an expert on Byzantine chant, extra canonical biblical literature.
or Byzantine church history, right?
Like all of these things, right?
Like those of us who have gotten a PhD
and become an expert in something, right?
Have one little slice, right?
And if you put all of us together in a room, right?
You've got a whole bunch of slices.
But I don't even think if you get all of us together
in a room, right?
Like seriously, like you get a room,
There may be a room like this in a few-
weeks close to it, right? You put me and and Father Joseph Lucas, and Dr. Bob Rancid,
and Dr. David Bradshaw, Dr. Eutham, and we can red down the list, right? Like all the
people you think of, it's like Orthodox scholars with PhDs in Eddie Field. If you put us
all in a room, I don't think we'd cover the entirety of the Orthodox tradition in
expert.
No, and there's some parts of it that are so specialized or so localized. Like, for
George and Orthodox history is a huge
subject, which almost no one in the West knows hardly anything about.
Yeah, yeah, just an example.
That's what I'm saying, right?
And so no one can master all of it.
I think many thousands, if not millions, of Orthodox Christians have lived holy lives,
gone on to their reward in Christ.
Without having ever read the entire text of the book of Ezekiel, let alone the acts of John.
one. Right. Accept it.
accepted. This is not the most important thing for you working out your
salvation, for you living the Orthodox life, it is not the most important thing.
Right? So I think that's fair. That's a fair point to make. Right? And if I thought,
if I thought for a second, I think I could honestly say this. If I thought for a second that the
sort of harshest knee jerk critics of this show were right.
And that we were starting...
some kind of weird faction within the church that was just obsessed with these
obscured-test ideas and weren't really Orthodox or weren't really embracing
the fullness of the Orthodox faith, I would stop doing this show. I don't think
that's remotely true. I don't think you guys are doing that. I think you guys are
Orthodox Christians who are just interested in this stuff. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And so
from my perspective, being an Orthodox Christian who's interested in this
stuff is no different than Big
North of Oxygen news.
interested in Byzantine Chan, or interested in George
Incher's history, or interested in the historical doctrine
of the Trinity, or interested in how the essence,
energy distinction works and say Gregory Paulibos.
We're all worth an oxfishing, and we have interests that
we invest relative amounts of time in different parts of
the tradition that are especially interesting or resonate
with us as particular people.
So that's why response to what I think is the good and
the fare.
objection. I think there's also the unfair and bad objection, which is based on just that our culture.
I don't even think that you could narrow it down to prodigism. I think our culture, I think this
is Plato brain. Our culture is just indoctrinated as this kind of binary thinking. Right of like,
This is Bible. This is not Bible. Right? Bible good, not Bible bad, right?
You know, every moment you spend, you know, having fun, you're not spending praying.
You know, every this kind of way of thinking where unless you are spending your time and your
thought and your resource and whatever on the most important thing, it's virtually simple.
Right.
And...
That's nonsense.
Yeah. Right.
Number one, no one actually can live like that.
But platonic metaphysics isn't real.
That's not actually how God constructed the world.
That's not how the world works.
And so, if it's just that, you know,
hey, this isn't in the Bible, so it's bad.
then, you know, there is a third possibility. And that is that I think there are particular people
who shouldn't read this stuff. Like there are particular people who shouldn't read the book of
Revelation. Yeah, and that's Bible. That's not to say there's something wrong with the book of
Revelation. It's just where they are at a particular place at time or the way their minds working
at the moment or certain tendencies they have as a person. If they start focusing on the book of
revelation.
spending a lot of time reading it, they're going to run off in a weird direction.
Right? And someone could do the same thing with the book of Enoch. So it could do the same thing
with the Filicalia, which is why some people get told not to read the Filicalia by their spiritual
fathers. Right? So there's that individual level too. And if somebody's spiritual father has told
them to stay away from this or that book, I'm not going to encourage them to read this or that book.
Yeah, right like so there's that too, but so that's my take
on that situation.
Yep.
All right.
Well, I hope that helps a bit, Paul.
Thank you very much for calling.
Thank you, Paul.
All right.
We're going to take another call.
So we have, I know I always have a sprang, but you've called before.
A noosh.
Yes, Father.
Okay.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Christ is risen.
Indeed he is risen.
Yeah, so I
You know, I tend to call, I was traveling and I'm in Chicago.
So I figured I'd do my usual call on the lot of space
from a different state.
So, okay.
Enough with that.
We're all over.
I mean, we actually have somebody listening from Egypt
tonight who commented on the YouTube chat.
So it's always amazing to me where people are listening
from Chicago, that weird exotic place,
almost as exotic as Egypt.
All right, all right.
All right.
Yeah, yeah. So yeah, so my question was sorry, there's some background noise. I'm gonna get away from the
question was related to
the book of Genesis. Oh
I think we lost the news. Are you still there? Yeah, sorry. Okay related to the book of Genesis
and uh
And wondering what the connection is, or maybe there's not, is the
the tree of life and Christ, because television comes to Christ
and he's this life.
And so I'm just wondering why the tree was there in the first
day for me.
Yeah, like what's the connection?
And what are your thoughts on that?
OK.
So I mean, the first thing I'll say is that the cross is very often
identified with the tree of life.
Because three
through the cross, in corruption, immortality, eternal life, come into the world.
And so it's really that the cross is the restoration of the tree of life.
But of course, it's Christ's cross.
And so, you know, we don't eat fruit of the tree.
We eat the flesh and blood of Christ, right?
And that is what, that is the medicine of immortality.
That is the food of eternal life, right there.
So I mean you're definitely tracking...
correctly father I don't know I mean there's so many things that can be said about this I feel
like whole books have been written about this question. Yeah don't don't forget the leaves.
This is a deep cut I guess I guess people don't know about this but if you read the Old Tesserere
Provincy, you read the book of Revelation the leaves of the tree of life have healing in them for
for the nations, which is why you may notice that the
cross as used most commonly in Orthodox crosses is the one that is blossoming.
Yeah, yeah.
Because we have as our self identity that we are the Gentile Church at this point.
Right?
And so that blossoming is the healing of the nations and being called back to God.
So, they...
that paradise is found within the church where the tree of life is.
Yeah. Yeah. Well, I don't know if we still have you a notice, but I hope that that that helps a little bit. Are you still with us?
Yeah, that really helps. I never thought about the connection with the leaves and the cross in the church. So that's really cool. Thank you again.
Yeah, yeah, sure. Thanks for calling. God bless you.
All right, well, so see finally someone called they took pity on you father.
Well, yeah, I mean, other ones have stuck talking to you for three hours every two. Right?
I mean, what do we have to talk about live it up a little bit?
So yeah, the acts speaking of live iting it up, here we go. They asked a job.
So we have this text, it's middle of the second century.
compiled by St. John's spiritual grandchildren at some indeterminate point after it's written
this
Nostek chunk gets shoved in there pretty awkwardly and obviously
And that version of the text comes into popular use among Nostek groups, including the mannequins
So when we're talking about the original text, right?
Because you know, I gave you a couple examples beyond that. I don't really care about the later insertion
That's not that interesting to me.
The original text and the traditions about St. John.
So this is going to escalate quickly.
I'm just telling you now.
Buckle up a little bit.
We're going to try and be as politic and as gentle as we can about this.
But well, it's stuff's going to do.
So
It begins with the king of, there's a king of Ephesus named Leicomedes.
And Leicomedes is married to a woman named Cleopatra.
Cleopatra dies.
And you remember what I was saying about the fragility of ancient people.
like a beauty's sort of pines to death and he dies too.
guys have a broken heart. Yeah. Yeah. Due to his wife having died. They're not
extremely elderly. They're not. It's not one of those things, you know. It's just fragile
constitution. I guess there were emo kids like in the mid-second century ruling
emphasis. But so say John comes and he raises the both from the dead.
Cleopatra first, right, so that we'd like to be used to the race of the dead. Cleopatra's alive.
He is so happy that he has a portrait icon painted of St. John. You may be guessing why this comes up
in the seventh, the medical council. And he has it adored with flowers and they like candles in
front of it, right? And so St. John hears about this, okay? And sort of comes back to see like a
I can be...
like a beauty says, oh, listen, I worship only God, but I also honor the God's Lord Ks. G for us,
who do his works and teaches word in this world, right? So he basically gives the distinction between
leadership and veneration right to St. John. So St. John responds
And this is widely open to interpretation.
We'll come back to this when we get to the Southern Greek Council.
But St. John responds by saying,
Percy says, well, you've made a dead image of a dead man.
Okay. But then he goes on to say,
say, John goes on to say that what...
What Christ really wants is for Leica Medies to paint a portrait of St. John with his life
using his good deeds as the paints and the colors.
So, St. John effectively is saying to him,
him. The real way to honor me is not to like candles in front of my
picture, but to imitate St. John's life as he imitates Christ, right, to become a saint
yourself. You honor a saint by imitating them. You honor a saint by becoming a saint yourself,
right? And following their example, not just by outwardly honoring their image. Okay.
We'll come back to this. Um,
Say John then moves on.
He goes to the Temple of Artimists and
which of course is one of the seven wonders of the ancient world. It's still standing at this time.
For the moment, they're having the big feast, the big annual feast of Artemis.
St. John comes wandering in. He is not wearing the pagan festival garb, being not a pagan.
And so this makes the priests at the Temple of Artemis very upset. They get angry.
and St. Johnress.
He challenges them to a showdown.
Profit Elijah and the profits of bail style showdown.
Let's say, John says, I am going to pray to my God that you all die.
And you all pray to your God that I die and we'll see what happens.
I told you this was gonna escalate quickly.
Okay. So he just goes nuclear option, right? Like bring it, right? Now the to their to their the
credit of their intelligence at least the priests of Artemis have heard about St. John and the
miracles he's been doing and raising people from the dead and stuff and they're like, you know,
this will go badly for us. We do not accept your challenge. Right. They're not stupid, right?
whatever other faults they have. And so, uh, St. John did praise anyway and part of the
temple collapses and kills their hybrids. But the rest of them who are smart enough not to accept the challenge
they survive. Okay
things have not actually begun to escalate. Now's when you really need to buckle up. Stuff's about to get weird.
Okay
St. John continues his travels around. He's walking through a field.
He sees a guy running through the field carrying a sickle.
It's not exactly runs with scissors, but basically.
Yes.
You don't run with scissors or sickles, kids.
That's right.
No running with sharp movements.
But he's running with a sickle.
I learned what a sickle is because I read asterix in Oblix comics and the druid get a fix
was always cutting mistletoe with a sickle, a golden sickle, so he could make his magic
potion.
So that's how they're.
Yes, yes.
So you probably would not run with it.
No, in my head I always see get-a-fixes.
golden sickle, you know, that he used to cut this one.
So, uh, and this is why from an early age, you were indoctrinated in communism.
Um, so no, no, without the hammer, I'm safe, right?
Okay.
Um, so he sees man running with sickle.
This is an unusual thing.
Uh, so he stops the guy, Hey, you know, what are you doing?
Where are you going?
in with that sickle.
And so the young man who was running with the sickle says to say,
John, well, that he had been sleeping with another man's wife.
And his father had found out that he was sleeping with another man's wife.
He pulled him aside. It's his son can't be sleeping with other man's wives.
You're bringing disgrace to dishonor upon us and upon our family.
How dare you you need stop there?
you need to get back in line. And this young man responded by getting very
angry at his father and beating and kicking his father to death.
Well, and now having, having killed his father, having killed his father, he was now running
with the sickle to go and find the woman he had been cheating with her husband to murder
both of-
them and then take his old life presumably with the sickle.
And then say, John stopped him but you know he told him all this okay.
So I mean let me just clue you in now. A lot of the rest of this in the acts of John is just
going to sound like St. John randomly wandering into episodes of Law and Order SVU
Like halfway through.
So he's not going to kill everybody, right?
So St. John says, hey, hey, buddy, it's calm down.
If I go and I raise your father from the dead, right?
I'll raise your father from the dead.
If you agree, not to go murder anyone.
And the kid says, okay, I'll take that deal.
and so they go back and see
John raises his father from the dead. Okay. So okay, I, I, I
no longer have guilty of the murder of my father, technically,
because he's alive, even though he did murder him. Right. But
still the guilt, right? The guilt over what he'd done. The guilt
over having slept with his other man's wife. And that having
driven him to this horrible crime of killing his own father, he
can't deal with the guilt.
And he can only think of one thing that could be responsible for all this.
For having driven to do all this.
And so he takes the sickle and he castrates himself.
It's way don't run with scissors kids or sickles.
And then, I castrate himself, he runs again.
He goes and finds the woman with whom he had been cheating.
and fling
his severed genitals at her.
This is the first time that is the first time that sentence has ever been said on the
airwaves of ancient faith radio.
Very likely.
Likely the last also.
Flings in at her.
says that the thing which he has swung at she the woman are
got him into this whole mess.
Right through through the seduction of lust.
Okay.
So, uh, say, Jonathan finds the kid again.
It says, so self mutilation is also a sin.
Right.
Self-butilation is a-is-
is also said, and not only is it also a sin, but it is just as bad of a sin as the adultery
and the murder and stuff. Don't do that. Right? So we have an anti-originist element here to our,
to the axiom. You should, you should not do this and he says the real problem
is your thoughts. You need to learn to control your thoughts.
and not active pulsively. I think St. John's kind of right on on that one. The acting
impulsively is clearly this kids problem. But learning to understand your thoughts, right,
to control your thoughts and not to run off after these these various sins. Okay. So you might
think well okay tech sass to mellow out from here don't get excited yet
There's more coming.
So say John travels on. He decides he's moving on. He stops it and in.
The any stops at his bed is full of bed bugs. So he sort of dispels. He sort of exercises the bed box.
I mean, how many states you get with bed bugs?
Like, yeah, they'll cast out the bed bugs.
And then here's the next episode of Criminal Minds that he wanders into.
There is this town, there is this fellow named Kalamakas.
Kalamakas is, let's be honest, in lust more than love.
with a Christian woman, Kell Marcus is a pagan.
He's a lust after this Christian woman, Luciana, who is married to a Christian man named Andronicus.
Kalamakis, the pagan man, is a horrible sex pest.
And between his looted vances, etc.
he puts so much stress and anxiety on Luciana that she dies.
for all the stress at everything.
How to put this delicately, this does not discourage Kalamakis from wanting to sleep
with her.
Her being dead.
Yeah.
And so he goes with his servant, Fortu Nautis.
Miss Fortu Nautis.
if you're nasty.
No, they're just for Chodotis.
Goes with the for Chodotis
to steal her body
for these purposes.
As they go to do it,
a snake bites for Chodotis
and Kalabakas and kills them both.
The
state John comes into the scene.
raises everybody from the dead.
Hey, right.
Calabacus and Fortinatus and Luciana and Calls Upon Calabacus and Fortinatus to repent
of what they were up to.
And become Christians and they of course see now the error of their ways due to snake
bite.
Oh, now I understand that that was wrong.
ha ha ha ha
wow
Yes. So we had to be a little under detailed in that section for reasons that are probably
apparent to all listeners. It's because the bed bugs isn't it? Yes, the bed bugs. We didn't
want to create people out about the bed bugs. So then the final bit in the acts of John is about
the death of St. John. And this tradition about the death of St. John is also something that
we have a lot of independent attestation of.
So, when St. John reaches great old age, so he's like a hundred or older even.
He has revealed to him that the time has come for him to die, so he goes and he digs
his own grave and climbs into it and prays sort of his final prayer and trusting himself
to God and
the dirt comes in and covers him. And that is how he dies. And he's the only one of the apostles to not be martyred.
There are. So there's that version here in the acts of John in other versions of the story. It talks about the earth on the top of the grave still moving.
like maybe St. John is still alive in there.
Yeah, I mean, there's this tradition of...
It's often called mana, but I mean it doesn't mean mana like in the Torah, but they call it
mana anyways coming up out of his grave once a year and then people, this sort of dust
or whatever, people being healed because of that.
Yeah.
There's also a version where his disciples come out the next day and they find his sandals
laying there by themselves, like the rest of his, him has been assumed into heaven.
But you can compare those versions.
Left behind.
If you go and read the Sinek Sarian for September 26th
in the Orthodox Church on September 26th,
we commemorate the door mission of St. John the Theologian.
We'll follow you sleep, we'll say John the Theologian.
And you can read the Sinek Sarian there.
There is another version of the same story, right?
So this is a widely attested tradition
as to how.
So just coming back here at the end, we mentioned that the Axe of John got brought up at the Seventh
Ecumenical Council.
It was actually being used by the iconic class.
So the iconic class, this is the end of the eighth century, right?
They show up with a copy of the Axe of John.
I
So look here, this guy made an icon and was venerating it of St. John.
And in their interpretation, St. John rejected that.
And St. John rejected that.
And so see, this is proof.
This is proof that the apostles rejected icon veneration.
The council was like, huh?
And said, you know, first of all, no, that's not what's going on in the text. Second of all,
you're assuming this is like authentic, right? Like that this is 100% historically accurate
St. John. And then three, hey, look at this big Nostics section, right? In this text,
Literally, no sticks.
Ericky has a fiddle.
this text, right? So not only can you not assume it's reliable, we can kind of assume it's
kind of unreliable. And so basically they threw out that argument and they ordered that the
Yeah, conoclast copies of the acts of John B. Burnt.
Right.
So why don't we just have a thing?
Yes, here's the thing.
father Andrew mentioned to the caller. This book is on the list of St.
Nicophorus, a generation later, patriarch of Constantinople as him having
copies in the library, and saying it was beneficial to read privately.
Right. So that whole burning all the copies thing never happened.
Yeah. Now there may have been, right, a different, maybe there was an
even more nostic version than the one we have now.
And maybe that's the version that was burned,
maybe it was some particular version of the text
or something.
Or maybe it was just not carried out
because people pointed out there were other ways
to read the text or there were other beneficial things
in the text, right?
And of course, the fact that it's to be read privately,
right, you have to remember how low the literacy rate
was, right? Anyone who could read was...
probably either ordained or a monastic or both. Right? Meaning they had a context
and everything to be able to read and interpret it properly and deal with the text properly.
Right? So limiting it to those people who could read it in an appropriate way makes sense as a solution.
But yes, so that's how the text ends up becoming involved in the
the Seven Medical Council, but anyway you cut it.
Anyway you...
you cut it. Even if you say, even if you want to say, okay, this is just a straight out
Nostic text. And you want to read it in a Nostic way. For purposes of the 7th
Emechanical Council, let's say this is a Nostic text, right? Well then this is a
Nostic text. And let's say they were the Iconoclasts were reading it correctly.
Well, then you have a Nostic text from the middle of the 2nd century AD, critiquing
Christian icon veneration.
And anyway you read the text, you have the distinction between worship and icon
veneration being made by in a Christian text of the mid-second century.
Yeah.
Proving the antiquity of that idea, right?
So you take all that into account in terms of this text,
its relationship to iconoclasm.
And that brings us to the end of our second half.
Yeah.
All right.
going to go ahead and take our second and final break.
One more act.
That's right.
One more.
The final act.
It's the five.
Anyway, we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
We live in a world that commonly sees the passion of anger as a virtue that can be used
to help write wrongs.
But what do scripture and the fathers say about anger is expressing outrage at societal
ills a true reflection of God's attitude towards these evils?
Or does it instead blindest his presence?
Father, theater, Puccini, and Oswin Crateon joined together to examine how anger affects
our journey towards the illsons.
today at store.enginebase.com.
that's store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, we're back.
We actually had a caller waiting and he disappeared.
He disappeared.
But I will, if I remember correctly his question.
was because this is a good question. Like how do you distinguish between sort of different
kinds of apocrypha? You know because obviously, you know, we're making distinctions between
even portions of texts, right? That are gnostic. Yeah. It just reminds everybody, right? There's
there's canonical scripture, there's apocrypha which means you know, the stuff that's okay,
you know, good to be read at home privately or whatever. And then there's books that you should not read.
right? Yes. You know, so so how do you
like, you know, just kind of review that for us father. Like, what are these
distinctions and what's kind of a good way? I mean, I'm just going to plug your
book again. It's worth it because it covers all this stuff. But but just give a
short, a short outline there. Well, I mean, historically, the churches made
these distinctions for us. That's why I used St. Nicholas's list, which one of
one of the appendices of that book is just St. Nick Afford's list.
Right. So and he's actually got four categories. He's got books that are read publicly,
meaning canonical books, books that some churches read publicly and others do not,
which is interesting given that it's the ninth century. For the Old Testament he has exactly
what you might expect.
What are generally called the juduro canonicals are listed as old test...
that some churches read and not others.
But in the New Testament,
he's got both the apocalypse of St. John,
meaning the book of Revelation,
as a book accepted by some and not others,
even in the ninth century.
And also he's got the apocalypse of St. Peter there,
and a couple of others.
So I think we did an episode where we went through the apocalypse of St. Peter way back.
So but so there's that category.
Then apocrypha, right, meaning books to be read privately, which as I was just saying at the end of the last half.
The fact that they're going to be read privately means that the people who are reading them are going to have a
certain level of education and background at this kind of thing, but the fact that there
number one able to read and number two have access to the text.
And then there's the category of things not to be read, which would be called a band
book list, whatever.
Things that are identified as being Gnostic Junk, right, or other heretical junk.
And those books would generally be excluded from libraries and that kind of...
and when you have those listed, it's with a deliberate purpose.
It's, you know, a bishop will list those because it's like,
oh, I've heard there are people reading this and the churches.
This is not good. Go get rid of this, right?
Like, yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
Like if a bishop today found out that a bunch of parishioners
at one of his churches were reading from the New World
translation, which is the Jehovah's Witness Bible translation,
right? Like he might be like,
Yeah, yeah.
get rid of those guys. Right. Get yourself a KJV or something. Not just making like a list of
band books or whatever. It's about addressing actual things going on. Yeah. Yeah. There was someone,
you know, there were some ones reading this and something was happening and they say, hey,
this isn't one we want to be, right. We want to be reading. And so yeah. So
So...
The books that are listed as apocryphal by somebody, that is somebody, so for example, St.
Nicolphoris, saying out of his, he has the patriarchal library at Constantinople, right,
what are the sort of quasi-scriptural books, right, that are out there that I think there
is some value to reading. But that I don't believe in Scripture.
essentially right and so when I go and do a book like apographer or I talk about these texts that he
lists what I'm saying is right well here's a saint who suffered for the faith as a confessor who
was the patriarch of katsat nobel he considered that this is a book that has something worth reading in
it right so let's look at it and discuss it see if we could figure out what the things are that
that are valuable here that he would point to.
But this is it is.
Assessment that like East person is called to make for themselves
Right
Right, and this is important because this is a lot of our Protestant friends talk this way
If you push them on it, they'll admit it's ridiculous and not true
Right, but they'll say things like you know, oh well what I would I when I read these books and only these books I hear the voice of God
Right or the Holy Spirit
revealed to me that these books and only these books are scripture and that's
nonsense. Someone handed you a Bible. Yeah. The Bible is compiled centuries
before you were born. I'm talking about everybody. Orthodox, Roman Catholic,
Protestant, okay. You're handed a Bible, right? It has books in it. You're told
that's the Bible, okay? At some point later in your life you run into somebody
whose Bible is missing some of those books or who has more
books than you do. And you figure out what to do with that. But that's the, that's real
life. Okay. There is no one who was born with no concept of what a Bible even was. And you
went out and read every book ever written and determined purely based on the guidance
of the Holy Spirit, that these 66 books and only these are the Bible. Right. That's nonsense.
Right.
has ever done that. Okay? The question is this book canonical is not an open question.
It's not subject to discussion. It's objective fact. A book is either read publicly in your church
or it's not. Right. You can't really debate that. It is or it isn't. It's the same question as like
frankly, who is the saint of your church? It's in the list of your patriarchy or your
You know.
So your jurors, that's that's the list.
There this is an objective thing.
Yeah.
Okay.
You can do all kinds of special pleading, but it's an objective thing.
So this is why I mean, this show, since all we ever do on this show is talk about the book
of Enic, right?
Of course, right?
I gauge, you know, it was a book of Enic canonical.
Should we think the book of Enic is canonical?
I'm like, are you Ethiopian?
Yeah.
If you belong to the Ethiopian or Erician church, then the answer for you is yes.
Yes.
If you have some questions, are you an idiot?
Ethiopian is no then no, it's not canonical for you.
And for what I had given to understand from Ethiopian people,
even if you are Ethiopian, the answer is more like it's complicated.
But
right, but like the point being this is this is an objective thing.
Right. And it's something that was decided and settled long before any of us
listening or talking were born.
Yeah
Yeah, we got another question which is related to this was actually, you know,
could apocrypha ever be considered canonical. I mean, and you know,
obviously not. The question is, what does your church actually read as canon
in church services? That's what's canonical. Yes, so not now. Yeah, I mean,
Is it possible?
Yeah.
It's possible sometimes some
play. So whatever. Yeah, it's possible. In some cases. Yes. As you said, you see,
be as said that, was it you see, be as to said that some churches were reading the Acts
of Paul as a canonical book? Yes. You know, so it was come out for them. So like, so
there's, there's a doctor who audio drama where the eighth doctor asked to fight crampus.
And so he jumps to the Tartus that goes back in time and gets the actual St. Nicholas
from the 4th century.
And brings him forward in time to Vienna
to help him destroy a campus, okay?
But if he had detoured while he was in the 4th century
in Asia Minor, he could have gone into a church
where they read from the apocalypse of Peter.
Yeah.
And while standing in that church in the 4th century,
the apocalypse of St. Peter was canonical
in that church in the 4th century.
Yeah.
button.
So such church exists today.
Yep.
Yeah, exactly.
And this challenge is the reason people have trouble with this is it
challenges the view of candidacy that they have because the view of
candidacy that they have is tied up with this whole other set of ideas of
the inspiration of the Holy Spirit and this and that.
Yeah, it's a subjectification of the texts rather than how is the
situated within your church.
It's the text itself.
Right.
So the authority
is not in the text itself. The authority is in the church. It's the church's use reading
application of the text that is authoritative. We actually have to come up with books.
Yeah, it's a book and it is not ontologically different than other books. Take that.
one of the
actually have a couple calls that came in there about I don't know I don't want to use the word random half hazard
the bits
So we actually do have some that we want detailed questions about what we discussed in the last half so no indeed not be safer
Indie now so we actually have a caller coming all the way from Australia. So Christian from Australia. Welcome to Lord of Spirit spot
We hear you Christ is risen
You found a working phone in the atomic waste found.
A lot and sure would say.
So it's your question.
I had a question. I firstly, I wanted to tie up a loose end from the last conversation.
I had a few months ago on defending my use of the term platypide.
If you would indulge really here, my case, the platypide was the ultimate and big US creature.
I'm not sure if you've seen one in person before.
but it's not one animal.
It's a combination of many kinds of animals.
It's a mammal at Laïd-Egg,
there's a pletiposis, there's a fever,
there's a mouth, there's a thumb,
weed and fibrium, we don't know.
And I also too, and an anombicia with creature you see,
because mum's side is the Western Roman Empire,
and that's why it's Eastern.
So thus it is fitting that pletiposis
should be a merge of both Greek and Latin terms.
Yes, but English doesn't have to...
do that. Right, I think. Well, yeah, yeah.
This is the spot my schizophrenic rambling. It's a no it's a no
a noble. It's a noble try though. I will give you that it's a
noble thing you're trying to do. Plus if you say plan to
put it on airs. I say, well, it's like I one day in my
I rehearsed for the defense of the terms,
how to apply perhaps that may be successful but,
then regard.
that I have a question that's not terribly related to the topic at hand, but I just want
to pick Father Steven's brain about this because I can't.
Before you do, I have one more comment. I have one more comment on the platify situation.
Is this coming out of some kind of resentment of the English as an Australian?
No, I love the English. You know, they are very picky about that kind of thing. And I feel
like you wanted you're kind of doing the work in man.
the exiled you right and now you're
going to get back at them by offending
their refined grammatical senses.
My goodness, Steven Young.
I think I've just about aggravated everyone then.
The Greeks are not happy.
The Romans aren't happy.
The English aren't happy.
My goodness.
Oh, right.
Anyway, regarding today's topic,
it's final means for the students.
I think if you have anything to say as well,
but can't find any orthodox.
that in particular talking about in the gospels, when Christ is referred to as a carpenter,
I understand that there's some dispute about whether that means the literal timber work, whether
it means the builder or perhaps even a stone maistor. Would you be able to comment at all,
fathers on, if there's any scholarly orthodox content that you may know in regards to this topic?
I'm trying to crack me if I'm wrong, Father Sivin, but I,
the Gospels call him.
know, some people say he's the Carpenter's son. Obviously,
Kassant Joseph is a carpenter, but doesn't ever describe Jesus
himself as a carpenter? Well, it doesn't describe Joseph as a
carpenter either. The word in Greek is techno. Oh, he's a
maker. It's a craftsman. Yeah, essentially. And yeah, and I don't
know any particularly, I mean, there's a ton of journal
articles about this and
but I don't know of any that are from an orthodox author in particular.
But so within the context of, so Nazareth, we're talking about biblical Nazareth,
not modern day Nazareth in Palestine.
Biblical Nazareth was not in one location.
Pesent villages like Nazareth in Galilee in the first century.
moved around because the peasants were mainly working as laborers harvesting crops for landowners.
And so the village would kind of, it was more like what we would call a shanty town, it would kind of be sort of re erected as the harvest right moved around.
it would kind of move around within a specific area,
but it would move around within that area.
It was not...
fully a settlement. And so within that, St. Joseph's role within that community was that he was
sort of more like a craftsman, he wouldn't have been specialized, it would have been more like
we think of like a handyman. So he would have worked with wood, he would have also worked with
stone he would have worked with
various things. He would have been one of the people helping erect the shelters, break down things,
re-erect them, move them around, repair roofs, datching, right? All of those kind of things for the
other villagers. And that gives you an idea of the sort of poverty level we're talking about for
for Jesus and his family because...
Right, if you think, right, this village is primarily made up of these peasants who are getting paid basically to harvest crops.
So think farm workers, okay.
And Christ's father is getting paid by farm workers to work on and repair their homes.
Right.
He works for poor people.
So the fact that Christ also would have learned this kind of trade with it for his father,
his public ministry, remember, doesn't start till he's 30.
Yeah.
So I mean, it doesn't see this, but it's probably good conjecture that he would have.
So the ancient world, that's what everyone did.
Yeah.
You do what your dad does.
old enough you started assisting.
your father and working with him be that if you had a family farm it would have been doing that
right helping around the farm but I think we've talked about this on the show before one of the
political undercurrents going on in the background of the gospels is that by that point in the first
century 70% of the land in Judea and Galilee that wasn't owned by the Romans right the Romans of
of course took
whatever they wanted, but the land that wasn't directly controlled by the Roman 70% of
it was owned by the high priest in his family.
And they had used the temple tax to basically extort the land from the people who God had
given it to in the Torah.
And so those day labors in Galilee, like in Nazareth, those were the people whose families
originally a
owned that land and it had been given that land to farm it by God.
The Sadducees essentially had used the temple tax to extort it and take it from them.
And now we're employing them for pennies to harvest what had once been their own family's
land.
And should be according to the Torah.
And should be forever according to the Torah.
Yes.
Yeah.
With no Jubilee here in sight.
So yeah, that's kind of what's going on.
going on with the economics of Nazareth.
Interesting.
At the time of Christ, childhood.
We lost our connection to Australia there, but hopefully,
Christian was able to continue to listen.
So anyway, all right.
Well, acts of St. Thomas.
How about that?
So actually the chat wanted to know, is this the same thing
as the gospel of Thomas?
No, it is not.
It is not.
Yes, gospel of Thomas is a whole other thing.
Yes.
There's another potential.
future episode. Extra canonical sayings of Jesus. Yeah, right? Saying of Jesus
that aren't in the gospels. But that the church fathers refer to and quote.
There's more than you think.
Okay, so what happened to state I mean the tradition of course is that he went to
India. So is that what we're talking about here?
Yes, that's what we're talking about here.
Yes, that's the short answer.
All of our friends in the Malakar church are like, finally, finally.
Yes, here we go.
Your moment has come.
So, yes, so there is of course just this broad tradition that that St. Thomas went to India.
That's attested to all over the place, right?
Right, that's not again, that's not coming from the acts of Thomas.
Yeah, that's all over the place, right?
That St Thomas went to India.
Now, if you want to hear the worst counter argument in history to that, I can give it to you.
Go for it.
I'm always ready for a worst counter argument in history because in my Calvinist seminary days, I brought this up.
The bag.
it's a Thomas had gone to India.
I was told by a very intelligent man,
one of the professors there who I won't name
because he is very intelligent
and this answer will reflect badly on him
and maybe make you question that characterization.
Said to me, no, that never happened.
I was like, well, how do you know that never happened?
I said, I know it's not the Bible,
but I mean, there's all this attestation, right?
That this happened.
Why are you saying this was so much certainty?
He said, because the New Testament said,
that St. Paul was the apostle to the Gentiles. Wow. Wow. Therefore, if you say any
other apostle converted any other Gentiles, I guess we're winking at the whole
Cornelius thing, any apostle went to any Gentiles, then you're contradicting the
The Bible was the theory there.
I do not find this to be a compelling counter.
argument. But besides the absence of a good counter argument and the broad
base of this tradition, there's a very specific things that we now know for
certain. Yeah. One of the most important ones is that the acts of Thomas, the
text we're about to talk about, a lot of the action centers around a king named
and guandifer.
Okay. Uh, and until very recently, like within my lifetime,
everyone said, well, this is how we know that this is fake. Right.
There's no such king, guandifer. There's no record of any king named guandifer in India,
in any part of India, in the part of India we're talking about, never existed.
And therefore, this is bogus.
And then...
within our lifetimes. Archaeologically, they discovered a huge cache of coins. And guess
whose face and name was printed on them from the first century? King Guanda Forest.
about that. Oops. Right. Uh, this isn't just a
gotcha like, ha ha laugh at the scholars who assumed that absence of evidence met evidence
of absence. It goes beyond that, right? Because the only record we had of this king's existence
until the late 20th century was in the Acts of Thomas. Yeah. Was it stories associated with
the state top is going to India.
Otherwise, that name was lost to history until the late 20th century.
So that makes it very powerful evidence, right?
Because when and how would they have made this up?
How would they have known about this king in order to invent this?
Right?
Yeah. So in addition to King Gwandafer being confirmed, we have also now archaeologically confirmed,
we had a shadow of it out, that there were Christian churches, fully functioning Christian churches
with bishops who had ongoing relationships with bishops in churches in Mesopotamia by the year AD 200.
Okay, you could go today. I don't recommend it. I'm not advising you to do this. I know someone who did this though. You could go to Pakistan
and
because of course
What's now Pakistan was the western part of India before the partition
By the British
You could go to Pakistan and there are remains of churches
from the late first and early second centuries with Aramaic inscriptions
Christian churches.
Right? There to be seen that have been archeologically excavated. Okay? So, we know Christianity came
there in the first century. We have details about the history of that region of India
that were only preserved in these texts about St. Thomas. Right? This is a very strong,
This is about as good in terms of ancient history.
This is about as good of a historical case as you get.
For St. Thomas having gone to India.
Yeah.
Like you do not expect more evidence than this.
We believe a lot of things happen in the ancient world
where we have much less evidence than this.
Supporting it.
Right? But no one questions it.
Yeah.
So then we have to ask the question once again.
apparently someone in the chat did related to the gospel of Thomas. Is it Gostoc?
And this is especially an important question because it's not just the gospel of Thomas.
There's the dialogue of Thomas the contender. There's a whole bunch of Gostoc stuff with St. Thomas's name on it.
Right. So yeah.
Red flags go up. They're a lot.
A lot of folks as scholars out there who just blanket assume that anything with St. Thomas's name on it is anostic text.
Because, you know, if the acts of Thomas isn't, it's an exception. Right.
And on one hand, it's on St. Nicholas's list, so I want to say it's an exception. Right.
But it is at best ambiguous.
And here's what I mean by ambiguous.
And we're going to see specific examples of this as we go through the text.
But there are significant passages and elements of it that you can read in a
nostic way,
or you can read in a not-nostic way.
Because guess what related to what we were saying earlier about
about tax not being able to exercise authority by themselves.
you can read texts in different ways, right?
And so when I say that this text is ambiguous,
I mean that quite literally.
You can read it either way.
And neither way requires a whole ton of special pleading.
Right, in the sense that like, you know,
sure you can, like if you find
one of the Kookie Jesus mythicist people
God you
to. Friend of the show,
Bart Irman had a debate with what
at one point that's it's funny
to watch because there's
literally a point where Bart
Irman. He's tried to be
respected, tries to be
respectful. He always does
in debates, but he kind of
burst out laughing at the guy
because the guy says something
super ridiculous. But uh, and
this guy had figured out some
way to read St. Paul's epistles
So that they were...
talking about some kind of cosmic,
gnostic Jesus or something and not Jesus of Nazareth, right?
It's about as kooky to imagine, right?
So I'm not saying yes,
you can come up with some cock-eyed way to read
the acts of Thomas to make it orthodox or to make it gnostic.
I'm saying fairly plain common sense reading of it,
you could go either way.
There's stuff in it that's ambiguous enough,
So here's the first example,
and we'll see some more.
First example.
The way you would usually make this determination in fact, this is how scholars with St. Thomas literature in particular, make this distinction.
So St. Thomas is the twin, right?
Dittabas.
Yeah, I agree.
It's decided in the Gospels.
Thomas called the twin.
Right.
Thomas who's called Dittabas.
Thomas who's called the twin.
Okay.
So,
in general,
You're sort of bare-bones
typical orthodox historical reading of this is just, hey, St. Thomas had a twin brother.
Pretty, pretty clear cut straightforward. When you read Nostek texts, one of the
tells when you're reading a Thomas text that's Nostek is that it will say that
St. Thomas is Jesus to it.
Yeah.
Or like his mirror.
or something weird like that?
Well, it gets weirder.
Yeah, spiritual twin, right?
And in different, Nostoc text, this goes different ways.
So like in Thomas the contender,
like Thomas is a physical human,
and Jesus is like an ephemeral divine person,
and the two of them are twins.
Like he's the material part.
And Jesus is the immaturity part, right?
So you get weird.
like that. One of the NOSIQ, uh, uh, uh, uh, St. Thomas gets crucified instead of Jesus
because they're twins, so like they do a patty duke and like, switch places. Um, so there's
a lot of weird twins stuff like that, right? So okay, okay. So acts of Thomas, what does
Well, it says that it says that it says
Thomas is Jesus twin, right?
So you're like, oh, okay, wait, Radar goes up.
Is this, is this Nostek then?
But then it says, well, he's his twin in that.
He lived a life that was just like Christ.
Okay.
So it's like, well,
okay, so is that Nostek or is it just saying,
he lived his life in imitation of Christ, right?
like he's a saint.
This is what I mean by ambiguous.
Right.
Like it's not totally clear.
But that means that you're not going to find sort of like that piece that got added to
the acts of John, which is blatant in your face.
Like, hey, guess what?
Jesus wasn't tangible some of the time.
You know, I mean, like there's not stuff like that, right?
That's blatantly nostic.
But there's also not anything that's like.
like, hey, the incarnation is real, right?
Like the other way, either.
So the acts of Thomas begins with Christ
selling Thomas into slavery.
Literally.
So, yes.
So.
So...
King Gwadifer has said one of his officials westward to Syria to find slaves to work out building his new palace.
And so Christ appears to the servant of Gwadifer and cells, St. Thomas to him as a slave,
as a workman to go oversee the building.
of King Gwadifer's palace, and that's how St. Thomas gets to India. The idea here in the
tax seems to be trying to drop parallels to Joseph being sold into slavery by his brothers
and going to Egypt. Right, and then of course once he's in Egypt he kind of works his way into
Pharaoh's court. It seems like they're trying to do a parallel there in the narrative. That's what's
going on with Thomas Goyle, there's a slave. But so as
say Thomas arrives in India, the first thing he does is disrupt the princess wedding.
King Guadifer's son is getting married and they're having this sort of pagan marriage
procession that's going to culminate in this big feast and say Thomas runs in and breaks
it all up. Sort of ruins the wedding of the wedding feast, okay. So here's another
Everything.
So the folks who are on the, this is a Gnostic text side, go see, this is anti-marriage.
Say Thomas hates marriages and weddings and doesn't want people to get married.
On the other side, this is a pagan wedding.
stuff is going on. That feast at the end is all food offered to idols.
to Hindu idols, India. So, is St. Thomas just breaking up the idolatry and the paganism?
Right? Not entirely clear in the text. Right? You could, you could kind of go either way with it.
So despite getting really mad about this, about a sun's wedding being broken up, gig
God if he has been assured that...
St. Thomas is this master workman.
And so, St. Thomas agrees to build the temple for King Gwadifer.
And so he gets the money.
And then he keeps coming back to King Gwadifer over and over again
and being like, man, I need a little more money.
I need some more money.
Just a little more money.
We're almost done.
Okay, I need some more money.
And finally, King Gwadifer gets suspicious
and sends somebody to find out what's going on.
And he finds out that St. Thomas is just taking all the money.
He gives.
and giving it to the poor and then preaching the gospel to them and baptizing them and stuff.
Right? So the Hall of St. Thomas back in front of him says, what are you doing? You take all
his money? You bamboozled me, right? You're you're taking my money and giving it to the poor. You
You have it built a thing, right?
You haven't put a single stone out there.
And say.
Thomas says, Ah, King, I have been building you a beautiful palace in heaven with the good
deeds I have been doing in your name, right? And King Gwaddover says, bull and prosubid
prison. Right. I'm not interested in that. Yeah. He's like, I'm not followed for that.
Right. Yeah. Uh, throws him a jail. But then once he has thrown, uh, St. Thomas and
jail. Remember where Joseph ended up, right?
The King's brother dies.
This is one of the themes that all of these apocryphal acts.
People just dropping dead, right?
So the King's brother dies and when the King's brother dies, he goes up to heaven and he
sees the palace.
He sees this incredible beautiful palace in heaven and he asks an angel, hey, what's that
palace?
Oh, that's your brother's palace that St. Thomas built for him.
that he has waiting for him in the kingdom of heaven.
Okay.
And so miraculously the king's brother comes back to life and says to the king,
no, he's telling the truth, man, really.
Like I saw the palace, it's magnificent.
You should let him out.
So let's say Thomas out of prison, he gets baptized, becomes a Christian so that he can,
enjoy his palace.
in the life of the world to come.
So having now baptized the king, St. Thomas says,
well, my work here is done,
and King Gwannifer's kingdom by the way,
archeologically is exactly where you would expect it to be.
It was right on the border between India
and like...
Parthian like...
Persia, right? Like it's like right
Their territory, right? So the coins had
Gwandafer's face and name on the front and on the obverse side about half of them had Zeus and about half of them had Shiva
So it's sort of a meeting point between Greek speakers, right the Greek speaking Roman world
The eastern part of the stretch of the Roman world and India
Yeah, but his work is done in Guadifers kingdom and so he decides to move on to the kingdom of Misdeus
Which is the next the next kingdom over?
There's not a united India at this time
and so
He hits the road
To head there now a major thing in the acts of Thomas that you see a lot more like the acts of John
There's lots of resurrections lots of raising the dead in the acts of Thomas. There's tons of exorcisms
As you might expect, if he's the first person bringing the gospel to the pagan India, right?
Where they're practicing pagan Hinduism, there's gonna be a lot of demonic possession that he's right,
gonna have to deal with.
But kind of the most amazing episode of this happens on the road where he runs into what in Hinduism would be called a Naga,
this serpent being creature, the serpent man on the road.
this serpent man identifies himself as number one the serpent from the garden of Eden. Number two, the angel who led the other angels in seducing the human women to create the Nephilim.
And number three, the spirit that possessed Judas when he betrayed Christ.
So basically San is the devil basically right yeah but
Those are the three specific identifiers he gives for himself.
Okay.
Listen, Aga.
And the, and as St. Thomas finds him,
he's just bitten and poisoned and killed this dude.
Okay.
So St. Thomas forces this creature to bite the guy
bite the guy he just killed again and suck all the venom out.
suck all the venom back out. And so he does this, he sucks the venom back out. The guy he had killed
comes back to life. And the the Naga who has sucked back up his own venom explodes.
Yeah. I mean, I feel like that's, you know,
So I'm seeing a 1970s or 1960s.
Doug McClure film, you know, like I feel like this is special effects of that sort.
Exploding team in surface.
I don't know.
Bollywood could do a lot with this too.
Absolutely.
It's a big song and dance number to go with it.
Naga's song and dance number.
Yeah.
Big time.
And then it ends with him exploding.
Yeah.
And I don't know if they collected the pieces and made like a jacket out of it because
that would be Naga Ha-
Why? Why, why is I not prepared for that? But so the next the next thing that
happens fortunately because he's still got a long road ahead of him to get to
the kingdom of Miss Deis is he runs into a donkey
and that the donkey agrees to...
carry him the rest of the way to the next kingdom. And when I say agrees to carry him, I mean that literally because this is a talking donkey.
Yeah.
I mean in my head talking donkey's always sound like any Murphy.
Even Balam's ass.
Yes. Well, and that's important because why could this donkey talk?
According to the Acts of Thomas, he is descended from Balam's ass.
Hey, we've been talking all this time.
So yes, so technically the book of numbers never says that God took away the power of speech
from that donkey.
And apparently according to the Acts of Thomas, he had passed the ability to speak on to his progeny.
And so now some 1500 or so years later, there is this race of talking dokeys.
Docky is one of whom.
So now we're going to carry St. Thomas to the kingdom of Miss Dei.
Yes. He does a lot more exorcisms on the way. A lot of these exorcisms involve women.
There's this trope here of women becoming demon possessed and the demons possessing them,
forcing them into acts of public ludeness and sexuality. This is probably connected to
certain forms of ancient Hindu pagan worship and that kind of thing in the area, which is
here being characterized as demonic.
Finally, he gets to the kingdom of Misedaise, and there we get a little more information
about the pattern of his ministry there, which takes the form of he will go to a place,
he will do miracles.
Those miracles, then, what's they have gotten people's attention?
This pattern should be familiar from the canonical acts of the apostles.
Well, so's miracles have gotten people's attention who will use them as an opportunity.
to preach the gospel to those people, when those people accept the gospel, he baptizes them and then celebrates the Eucharist with them.
So that is the pattern, right? One of the important things to emphasize again, this is the earliest layer of Christian tradition.
and what we see here is that what it means to be a Christian once you accept the gospel is
conceived into these sacramental terms.
You're baptized and then you join this sacramental life of the church.
There is no sort of, oh, you're a Christian now.
Here's a Bible.
See you later.
You guys should get together and talk about it once in a while.
Right?
These structures are put in place.
the acts of Thomas and what we would expect to see frankly from what we know.
historically about the first and second and third century church. Most of his
converts are actually women. I mean that's, it was in the early days.
Majority women and that's the case in the Roman Empire as well. And we even get
the names of a couple of the early bishops, which I probably mispronouncing
because these are like Hellenized forms of ancient Indian names, but
CIFOR and Usenies.
I'm sure there is an Indian form of those names that that's covering for in Greek.
Sam's skirt at that point, I'm sure.
So, but Cypher and Usidies are identified.
The reason I say they're early bishops is they're identified as people whom St. Thomas makes
his successors in particular places when he moves on to the next place.
Yeah, right. So they're literally there's sort of apostolic succession happening.
with these with these bishops. Once again, you see church structures here already as part and parcel of
evangelism and preaching the gospel.
And so then at the end of the Acts of Thomas, we get a series of hymns. The longest and most prominent one the one everybody talks about is called the hymn of the pearl
And the human of the pearl is another
one of these ambiguous texts. It's a poetic text, right? And basically it
poetically tells the story of this son who is sent by his father to Egypt to
get a pearl. This very valuable and beautiful pearl. And while he's there, he's
seduced by the Egyptian gods and de-worshiping them and he's seduced by the
women of Egypt into. Spending time with them shall we say,
And he sort of forgets about his mission.
And then his father sends him a letter that reminds him of his mission.
And he goes and gets the pearl and returns home to his father.
Okay.
Now you may be hearing this and you may be thinking,
well, that sounds dastic.
And that could be a fair reaction.
There's a gospel of the pearl in the dog of AdiTex.
You can read this in an elastic way where this is
about you know, sort of you are one of the sons of God.
You have fallen into the material world and become distracted by things like
sex and you know, relations with women and the religions of this world
and forgotten your true identity and your true purpose.
But now we've got, you know, the secret doses, the hidden truth, the pearl,
We can reveal it to you and you can return to
divinity or oneness with everything or whatever, right? You could read it in that kind of
nostic way. You could also, however, look at it and say, you know, this is kind of a smushing
together of the parable of the pearl of great price and the parable of the prodigal son.
Right? Like tropes from both of them. You know, this could just be about, you know, you have
of a mission and a purpose in life.
Right, the gospel is the pearl. Right, it will allow you to break away from sins like idolatry and sexual
immorality, which we've seen pagan India, just like pagan Rome was prone to. Right, you can break
away from these and come back to the God who created you. Right, you can read this in an Orthodox
way too. Right, and you can throw it. Why is it Egypt? Well, the whole symbolism, we were talking
about Joseph before the whole symbolism of the Exodus, right?
to go back to Egypt. We had it better. Right. The whole symbolism of Egypt in the Old Testament.
You can perfectly well read this in a North and Oxway also.
So for beginning to end, acts of Thomas, very interesting. Lots of good stuff.
Is it Nostek? Can be if you want it to be. Yeah. Can you read it in a North and Oxway? Sure.
And that's a good reason for it to be on a list of books that are read privately.
So you could make sure that people read it the right way and set it the wrong way.
Yeah.
Well, I mean, I've been trying to think about what kind of stuff I might say in terms of my own conclusions,
I would sort of tie all this stuff together.
I mean, there's not a single thread.
I mean, there's definitely a theme of like anti-nosticism in some of these texts.
But of course then, there's some.
It's like, well, if you really want to read it in an elastic way, you could.
But
To me, the more important thing, because it's interesting, we got a lot of questions
about like, well, how do you think about texts like this at all?
You know?
So I think what this does for us is it illustrates that there are a lot of different elements
of Orthodox tradition that should be treated differently.
you know, and for those who are influenced, we're not just
influx.
I mean, grew up in swimming in what is still frankly a basically Protestant culture.
It could be difficult to sort this out, which is why I think we got multiple questions about this.
Because, you know, most Protestants have been taught, look, the Bible is the one really reliable thing.
It's true.
Everything else is kind of, well, which of course we've taken that apart and shown how that doesn't really work.
And so then the question is, okay, well, what am I supposed to do about?
text like this. I mean, number one, there's obviously a lot that's in these that has become
part of the traditional one could also almost say in a certain sense canonical, not like
scriptural canonical, but canonical life of some of these saints. Like, if you look up
in the synchsalion, which historically anyways has had an actual liturgical function, you
know, parts of these being read during orthros. If you look up in the synchsalion, the lives
of some of these things.
you'll see some of the same elements are in there.
Not necessarily all of them.
Not necessarily all the same elements,
but the sum of the same elements.
And so often what you'll see in the
synxodian versions of these lives
is they tend to be kind of trimmer
and more restrained in some ways.
It's not that they're cutting out by any means
like miraculous stuff because
St. Slides are full of miracles.
So there's no problem like that.
The question is just sort of, well, how reliable, how well, you know, based are the sources,
you know, that are being used in putting together. Because the lives of saints that are in
this in Exodia tend to be a kind of compilation of traditions. And so the question is, you know,
like how reliable are they? So when you read stuff like this and you read like, you know,
a story about Jesus selling Thomas into slavery.
How literally are we supposed to take that?
Or, you know, say Paul baptizing a lion.
We're not.
You don't have to take that literally.
It's okay to just say, okay, this is a valuable story
that teaches me certain kinds of things.
That doesn't mean that we just simply say,
oh, it's all allegory, you know,
no, that really happened.
It's all just kind of make-believe stories
to teach us a lesson.
No, that's not true.
But the problem is is that when you try
to apply the question of...
of sort of the dogmatic filter to everything,
then you're gonna miss the point.
You're gonna miss the point.
There are, this is the truth.
There are saints lives that were self-consciously fictional
and even made their way into the synchsalion.
I've had a couple of conversations
and just recently heard another conversation
with someone else with a Tecan Nicholas Kotar
talking especially about a saint named Averkios,
who the only thing that was known about him
What's his name?
but it was needed to read his life during Orthross.
And so, hogg-yographers created a life of Saint Averkios
based on elements from other St. Slas,
so that there would be something to read
at the appropriate time during Orthross.
So it was very self-consciously a work of what we would call fiction.
But it sits there in that slot,
not just because the slot needs to be filled,
but because the point is to edify the listener
So that he can
be repent so that it can be a better Christian. And that is ultimately the point of reading
any of these texts. The question, did this literally happen or not, is not the right question
to ask of these texts because that's not why they're written. I'm not saying that ancient
people had no concept of fiction and nonfiction. Absolutely, they understood that some things
were fiction. Absolutely. And they also had no problem sometimes mixing the two together
to produce a netifying story. That's okay.
It's all right.
I mean, this existed in the Jewish tradition.
You have midrash, right?
Sort of filling out these stories for the purposes of commentary,
for the purposes of directing people to living life
according to God's commandments correctly.
So, you know, it's okay that...
And in those cases, like, these are...
Most of these are really early texts,
it's okay that even saints lives it.
that you don't get transmitted over centuries and start to acutely stuff along the way. That's okay
It's okay
Because the point of saints lives is not to say
Now this is a blow-by-blow
account of what happened and if you don't believe that you're anathematized
No, that's that's not how these texts function. That's not their purpose at all
right
Like I mean another good example that that's pre-Christian
and
like the story of Joseph and Asinith, the elements that are from Scripture in
there are pretty small compared to most of the story that's there. So it's
basically a kind of historical fiction and that's okay, right? It's written to be
edifying. I'm not saying it's written to be pure allegory or anything like that,
but it is written to be edifying like we have genres like this, okay? So these
text that we've looked at this.
are not canonical saints lives, they're not.
That's not what they are.
There are canonical saints lives.
Canonical, again, not in a sense of being read as scripture,
but being read as part of the church services,
connected with the church services,
put together collections of lives of saints,
this kind of thing.
And they tend to be much more restrained,
but even then the question that we approach saints lives with
is not could this satisfy?
a 19th, 20th, 21st century secular historians requirements for what they would consider true and not true.
The reality is, as most of the time, it probably is true in that historical sense.
I have little reason to doubt that.
But it's still not the right question.
If you're so busy asking whether this is sort of dogmatically true or not,
you're missing why these stories are written.
They're written so that we can be formed in the
the atmosphere of the church so that we can have the mind of Christ
him looking at the examples of the saints
and and imitate them where it's appropriate.
It's not always appropriate to imitate every saint in every
way, its just that.
Like, please kids most of you are not meant to live
up on top of pillars like St.
Simion's.
The style I said that's just not what you're supposed to do.
But nonetheless we can see the kind of drive for holiness
in the lives of even people like that.
And so that's really the point.
of what's going on and all these things.
And there's some wild, wild elements.
And honestly, I mean, some of that's what keeps you coming back.
And you want to know more, you want to hear the rest,
you want to connect.
And the truth is, of course, that if you look at other kinds
of texts from this period and even throughout the history
of the church, there's not really much that's actually
unusual there.
It's weird to us.
It's 21st century people.
But it's not weird to most people throughout history,
not most Christians, for sure.
So
Yeah, that's my understanding, one understanding of how to kind of understand these texts.
So at the present time, among people who identify as Christians, at least in the Americas,
Probably the least part.
popular phrase is extra ecclesiopoleusial of noiseless. Outside of the church there is no salvation.
It causes a lot of our friends anxiety and distress. Anyone who says it is some kind of weird exclusionary bigot and bad person.
But
The truth that that phrase is trying to express is exactly the theme where we started tonight,
and kind of where we ended up, which is that as it says at the beginning of the canonical acts
of the Apostles, St. Luke's Gospel described everything that Christ began to do and to teach.
and the teaching of Christ and the works of
Christ then continued in and through his church, his body in the world. The church is how Christ
is present and working in the world today. And so all salvation comes in and through the church.
because all salvation comes in and through Christ.
It's logical, corollary.
So the question is not about, is any individual person who is not a
communicate member of the Orthodox Church saved? That's not the question.
The question is, anyone in the world who has saved, how does their salvation come to
them? Comes to them through the Orthodox Church?
It's true historically.
It's literally the Orthodox Church that copied the New Testament in Greek all through the
centuries.
So we have it today.
It's how we got the Bible.
It's how we got church structures.
It's how the Gospel got preached, right?
Just historically it's true.
It's the source.
But what the book of Acts in the New Testament and what the other extra biblical texts that
that we read uh...
tonight also point out is that it's true at a very existential and experiential level.
How did Christ come to the city of Rome? He came to the city of Rome in the person of St. Peter
was an apostle of the church.
The came to Rome and started preaching baptizing people.
celebrating the Eucharist, established Bishops as his successors. How did Christ come to India?
The person of St. Thomas, one of his apostles, who came there,
preached the gospel, baptized people, celebrated the Eucharist, appointed Bishops as his successors,
created the structures of the church. Those structures of those Bishops then continued the ministry
That's St Thomas.
done. That was the ministry that St. Thomas received from Christ. Continue to teach Christ's teachings.
Continue to do Christ's work in those places. Continue to bring Christ's gospel to the next
kingdom and the next kingdom and the next kingdom and to the next generation and the next generation and
the next generation. We read about some pretty extreme situations.
the acts of John. They're kind of extreme to the point of almost comedy, right? You could
probably detect it the way I described them. Part of that was to diffuse just how horrific
some of them were. It sexually gross some of them were, right? But I've been at this game
a while in terms of being a priest and let me tell you there are real life situations that
extreme that happen in the world.
There are people you know who have been through, come through, been exposed to situations
that extreme involving sexuality and violence and things during their life.
They don't go around talking about it for obvious reasons.
And what we're reading about is...
in the acts of John with St. John walking into those episodes,
is St. John bringing Christ even into those incredibly dark,
incredibly sinful situations.
And by bringing Christ into them, he transforms them.
People who were dead are made alive.
people who were that had gone down the most green
Revis almost unimaginable road of sin turn around and repent.
And so this raises the question, if Christ is going to come into your family, your workplace,
Your school.
Your circle.
Sir.
of friends. How's he going to come there? He's going to come there through you. If you are a member
of the church, then you are a member of the body of Christ. You are one of the members, one of the
organs or the instruments through which Christ is working in the world.
And the one who's designated for Christ to work through in your world.
The people you know, the people you encounter, the people you work with, people you're related to by blood and by choice.
Just for those people to find salvation, they're going to find it in and through the chair.
Whether you want to accept it or not, whether you want to think that way or not, you're the designated member of the church who's assigned to them.
The missionary isn't about, you don't have to go into the depths of pagan India and start for scratch like St. Thomas after being sold at a slavery.
Right, you don't have to travel very far.
at all for your mission field, for the place where you're called to bring Christ.
And that's, I think, the thing we need to take away from these acts, even from the crazy and fabulous
stories. There are places of quiet desperation, sadness, darkness, sin,
in stored at sexuality, all of these things,
all around us, right here.
The
quote-unquote Western world.
People who desperately need Christ,
they need to hear the gospel,
need to get baptized,
need to come into the church,
lives need be transformed.
They're virtually dead,
they need to come back to a new life.
And each of us has the privilege,
at least potentially,
of being the vehicle the instrument.
through which Christ does those great works.
So that's what I have to say to some of this.
Amen.
Well, everyone, that's our show for tonight.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live this time,
we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us, Lord of Spirits at Ancient Faith.com.
You can also send a message to our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com,
slash Lord of Spirits.
And if you have basic questions
about Orthodox Christianity,
or you need help finding a parish,
Go to Orthodox.
intro.org.
Then join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
at 6 p.m. Eastern, 3 p.m. Pacific.
Suspicion's rising, answers aren't clear.
I thought we made a promise.
Now you've disappeared.
And if you're on Facebook, you can also follow our page.
You can join our discussion group and leave ratings and reviews and share the show with
the front.
And finally be sure to go to exit
faith.com, stroke support and help make sure we lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air. You seem to lead two lives at a time. Do I still
fit in? I thought you were mine. Thank you good night, Chris Ciserson.
You've been listening to the Lord of spirits with Orthodox Christian
priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a
for the listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11.